<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second sermon, preached at Paules Crosse, the 21. of May, 1598. vpon the 21. of Math. the 12. and 13. verses concluding a former sermon preached the 4. of December 1597. vpon the same text. By Iohn Hovvson, student of Christes-Church in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Howson, John, 1557?-1632.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03764</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13883</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121034</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856225</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856225</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21754</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03764)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21754)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 248:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second sermon, preached at Paules Crosse, the 21. of May, 1598. vpon the 21. of Math. the 12. and 13. verses concluding a former sermon preached the 4. of December 1597. vpon the same text. By Iohn Hovvson, student of Christes-Church in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Howson, John, 1557?-1632.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 52, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Arn. Hatfield for Thomas Adams, dwelling in Paules Churchyard, at the signe of the white Lion,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at Paules Crosse.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21754:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21754:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Second Sermon, preached at Paules Croſſe, the 21. of May, 1598. vpon the 21. of <hi>Math.</hi> the 12. and 13. verſes: Concluding a former Sermon Preached the 4. of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember 1597. vpon the ſame Text.</p>
            <p>By IOHN HOVVSON, Student of <hi>Chriſtes-Church</hi> in <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Arn. Hatfield</hi> for <hi>Thomas Adams,</hi> dwelling in Paules Churchyard, at the ſigne of the white Lion. 1598.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:21754:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21754:2"/>
            <head>A Sermon preached at Paules Croſſe, the 21. of May 1598. vpon the 21. of Mathew, the 12. and 13. verſes, by <hi>Iohn Howſon,</hi> Student of <hi>Chriſts-Church</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>The Text.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>And ſaid vnto them, it is written, Mine houſe ſhall be called the houſe of prayer; but ye haue made it a denne of theeues.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATH. 21. verſe 13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR bleſſed Sauiour in the 12.<note place="margin">Luc. 12.42.</note> of S. Luke 42. noteth it to be the office &amp; duty of a faithfull &amp; wiſe Steward, of a Steward or diſpenſour of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of God,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> as S. Paule calleth him, to giue vnto the houſhold in due ſeaſon their portion of meate, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the meaſure of wheate, which is due vnto them.</p>
            <p>By the meaſure of wheate ſaith S. Greg. <hi>exprimitur mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus verbi;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. paſt. li. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> the meaſure and proportion of the word of God is ment and expreſſed, which ought to be giuen to thoſe of the houſhold: which meaſure and proportion conſiſteth in theſe points, ſaith Eraſmus,<note place="margin">Eraſm. epiſt. ad Iod. Ionam.</note> 
               <hi>Promere cum res poſtulat, cui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> promere quod eſt accommodum, &amp; promere quod ſatis eſt:</hi> In deliuering the meate or the word in due ſeaſon,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21754:3"/>
at a fit houre; in deliuering that which is good and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome; in deliuering that which is ſufficient, not too little, nor too much: for in our corporall foode or dyet we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue theſe three things, a fit time to eate in, the good qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and conuenient quantitie of our foode.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 32. Cant. 7. Iere. 4.</note>I cannot ſay with Iob that <hi>I am full of matter,</hi> nor with the Spouſe in the Cant. <hi>my belly is as an heape of wheate;</hi> ſo that I ſhould be faine to cry with Ieremy, <hi>ventrem meum doleo, ventrem meum doleo: oh my belly, my belly,</hi> or with Iob, <hi>my belly is like the wine which hath no vent, and like new bottles which breake:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 6.13.</note> but with the men of Bethſhemeth, <hi>I haue reaped a little wheate in the valley,</hi> where though I haue not ſeene ſo much as the back parts of God, as Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes did (for that was on a mountayne) yet with them of Bethſhemeth I haue ſeene his Arke, that is his Goſpell, which hath in it both Manna, a word of comfort, and Aarons rod, a word of reproofe: which how I haue diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto you here to fore, either in regard of the due ſeaſon, or in reſpect of the qualitie of the wheate or ſuſtenance, <hi>vos ipſi iudicate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> you muſt be iudges. But leaſt I ſhould be offenſiue in the quantitie of it, I made an end <hi>vbi finis non erat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> where there was no end, as <hi>S. Barn.</hi> did, and all other Stewards haue bin forced to do,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.12.</note> being ſtraightned as our Sauiour Chriſt was, when he ſaid, <hi>Multa habeo dicere quae non poteſtis portare modo, I haue yet many things to ſay vnto you, but ye cannot bare them now;</hi> not by reaſon of the depth of any myſteries I had to deliuer, or in regard of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of your vnderſtanding (as he was ſtraightned) but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe with ſomewhat long ſpeaking, you were made, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Hebr. 5.11. <hi>Greg. paſt. li.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>weake or weary with hearing:</hi> for as <hi>S. Greg.</hi> ſaith, <hi>dum auditoris animus plus qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> valet tenditur, mentis chorda rumpitur, When the eares of our auditors are ſtrained beyond their accuſtomed compaſſe, the ſtrings of their attention will
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21754:3"/>
breake aſunder.</hi> Wherefore ſeeing they which haue pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and authority to commaund, haue ſaid vnto me as it is in the 17. of the Acts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act. 17.</hi> Bern. de conſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>we will heare you againe vpon this text, recurrat ſtilus ad ſuam materiam,</hi> as <hi>S. Bern.</hi> ſaid, I will returne to that part of my text where I left, without repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that which is paſt, ſauing only thus farre, that it may pleaſe you to remember, that I deuided this text <hi>in factum, &amp; dictum;</hi> into a deede of our Sauiours, and into a ſpeech of his; into an action of his, and the reaſon of it; the action was contained in the former verſe, and was a reformation of certaine abuſes in the temple, in which I obſerued fiue circumſtances, firſt, the author <hi>who,</hi> ſecondly, the time <hi>when,</hi> thirdly, the place <hi>where,</hi> fourthly, the matter <hi>what,</hi> fiftly, the manner <hi>how</hi> this reformation was performed.</p>
            <p>It remaineth now that by your accuſtomed patience I ſhould ſpeake of his ſpeech, which contained the reaſon of this action. The reaſon why he exerciſed this whip, this extraordinary and miraculous violence againſt them, was becauſe they had abuſed the temple and prophaned it; which he proueth by two texts of ſcriptures, the former taken out of the 56. chap. of Eſay, which ſheweth the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vſe of the temple, and the chiefe end of erecting it, <hi>My houſe ſhall be called the houſe of prayer:</hi> the latter is taken out of the 7. of Ieremy, and ſheweth the abuſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation of it; <hi>Ye haue made it a denne of theeues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I intreate of theſe particulars ſomwhat in generalitie of this ſpeech of our Sauiours; I deuided this parcell of ſcripture into <hi>factum,</hi> and <hi>dictum,</hi> an action, and a ſpeech,<note place="margin">Act. 1.</note> as S. Luke did all our Sauiours life into <hi>facere</hi> and <hi>docere;</hi> and whether were more myraculous <hi>opera diuina,</hi> or <hi>celeſtis doctrina,</hi> his diuine actions, or his heauenly ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, I will not diſpute, but greater teſtimonie was not giuen to his actions then is recorded of the Euangeliſts to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21754:4"/>
be giuen to his doctrine. For if he diſcourſed and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to the people either of the reſurrection of the dead,<note place="margin">Math. 22. Luk. 20. Ioh. 10. Math. 12.</note> Math. 22. or of Meſſiah the Lord and ſonne of Dauid, Luke 20. or of the ſonne of God by nature Ioh. 10. or the ſonnes of God by grace Math. 12. of the ceremonies of the lawe,<note place="margin">Math. 15.</note> or the works of charitie and mercy Math. 15. of the precepts of God,<note place="margin">Math. 22. Math. 5.6.7.</note> or the precepts of men Math. 22. of the firſt and greateſt commandement, Math. 5.6.7. of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the kingdome of this world, and the inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the kingdom of heauen Ioh. 3.<note place="margin">Ioh. 3. Math. 12. Ioh. 7.</note> of the paſſion Mat. 12. death and reſurrection of the Meſſiah Ioh. 7. of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the holy Ghoſt and the abundance of his graces: This was euer the iſſue &amp; effect and the witnes which his auditors gaue vnto the ſpeeches; <hi>Nunquam ſic locutus eſt homo ſicut hic homo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 7. Mark. 6.</note> Neuer man ſpake as this man ſpeakes, Ioh. 7. and in the 6. of S. Marke, <hi>Audientes admirabantur in ſermone eius, They that heard him were in admiration at his doctrine,</hi> that is, thought it miraculous; ſaying, <hi>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence hath he theſe things, and what wiſedome is this which is giuen vnto him?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 4.</note> and in the 4. of S. Lukes Goſpell, <hi>All gaue teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie vnto him,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>vvondered at the gratious vvords vvhich proceeded out of his mouth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> and in the 7. of S. Math. <hi>vvhen Ieſus had ended his vvords, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the multitude vvere aſtonied vpon his doctrine; for he taught them as one hauing povver, and not as the Scribes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If he plaid the reſpondent in diſputation, his anſweres were admirable, and put the diſputer to a <hi>non plus:</hi> When the Phariſes and Herodians diſputed about tribute to be giuen to Caeſar,<note place="margin">Luc. 20.</note> 
               <hi>they maruailed at his anſvvere, and held their peace;</hi> when the Saduces diſputed againſt the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, the Scribes wondered at his anſwere, and one of the Scribes ſaid,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Maſter, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, thou haſt ſaid excellently vvell;</hi> and when the Lawyer diſputed with him about the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21754:4"/>
greateſt commandement, after he had receiued his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, he confeſſed and ſaid,<note place="margin">Mark. 12.</note> 
               <hi>vvell maſter thou haſt ſaid the truth, and no man after that durſt aske him any queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If he vndertooke the oppoſers part, and diſputed with them, he vtterly confounded the wiſeſt of them: When he demaunded of the high Prieſts and the Scribes, who were the moſt learned among the Iewes, <hi>vvhether the baptiſme of Iohn vvere from heauen or from men;</hi> they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered plainely, <hi>they knevv not vvhence it vvas:</hi> and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he propoſed this queſtion to the Phariſes <hi>vvhoſe ſonne Chriſt ſhould be,</hi> and they anſwered him <hi>Dauids,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 20.</note> he ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, <hi>that none could anſvvere him a vvord,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Math. 22.</note> So that whether he ſhewed himſelfe a Schooleman as we call them, or a Preacher; whether he oppoſed, or anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or diſcourſed, his ſpeeches were as full of admiration, as miraculous, as his actions were.</p>
            <p>For whereas he was <hi>a carpenters ſonne</hi> reputed, Matt. 13.<note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> and had no other education, and therfore was called <hi>a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter,</hi> Mark. 6. nay, <hi>ille faber,</hi> a man noted by that trade:<note place="margin">Mark. 6.</note> whereas the Scribes which by the law of Moyſes were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed (as we tearme them) ſchoolemaiſters to inſtruct others (S. Auſt. calleth them <hi>grammaton iſagogos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. de ci. Dei lib.</hi> 18. <hi>ca.</hi> 39. Deut. ca. 29. &amp; 31.</note> the Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuagint <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Deut. cap. 29. &amp; 31. ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they taught the grammaticall &amp; hiſtoricall ſence of the ſcriptures) could teſtifie that he had not bin inſtructed by them: whereas the Phariſes, who were the chiefe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounders of the myſteries &amp; ſecrets of the lawe, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſate in Moyſes chaire, could truly affirme that he was none of their auditor; and therefore the Iewes could ſay with admiration <hi>quomodo hic literas ſcit cum non didicerit? hovv knovves this man letters vvhen he is not learned?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 7.</note> no ſcholler of the Scribes, no auditor of the Phariſes: yet where the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people of which he was one did ſpeake
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21754:5"/>
the Syriack tongue,<note place="margin">Euſeb. de de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrat. euang. lib. <hi>3.</hi> ca. <hi>7. Luke. 4.</hi>
               </note> as alſo his Apoſtles, and that only: <hi>Euſeb. de demonſtrat. euang. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. he could alledge a long text out of the 61. of Eſay in the Hebrew tongue, wherewith onely the learned were acquainted (as now adayes) and expound it and the moſt hidden and ſecret myſteries of the holy ſcriptures farre beyond the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nay beyond the capacitie and vnderſtanding of the Scribes &amp; Phariſes: and he that is well conuerſant in the holy ſcriptures, may perceiue that all the ſpeeches of our Sauiour Chriſt, haue either the perfect forme of a <hi>Cabala</hi> (as they call it) containing a moſt ſimple, moſt true, moſt deepe, moſt certaine expoſition of myſticall things in the ſcriptures; or elſe an auouching of ſcriptures themſelues; as in this place, where alledging a reaſon of his fact or action, he auoucheth the true vſe, and condemneth their abuſe by the ſcriptures themſelues; not without aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the auditors both Scribes and Phariſes, who as it ſhould ſeeme, could not reply, or durſt not make anſwere.</p>
            <p>Another note I obſerue before I come to intreate of his ſpeech in particular is this, that our Sauiour Chriſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming this action not as a man, but myraculouſly as he was God (as I ſhewed you before) would neuertheleſſe giue a reaſon of his action; whereas commonly with God <hi>Tota ratio facti eſt potentia facientis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ep. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>voluntas facientis: The reaſon of Gods actions are, ſometimes his power, ſometimes his vvill:</hi> and as <hi>humana conſuetudo verbis, ita diuina poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia factis loquitur, As we vſe vvords to expreſſe our mindes, ſo God by his actions ſhevveth his povver and his vvill alſo:</hi> and as new words or not ordinary phraſes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> 48. <hi>ca.</hi> 6.</note> being with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and decency inſerted to our ſpeech, <hi>ſplendorem addunt, do make them more pleaſing;</hi> ſo in Gods extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and miraculous actions, which euer in congruitie are very ſignificant, <hi>quodammodo luculentior eſt diuina eloquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21754:5"/>
God ſpeakes vnto vs more eloquently and ſignificantly then by other meanes;</hi> and the husbandman in the 20.<note place="margin">Math. 20.14.</note> of Math. who there repreſenteth the perſon of God, being asked by his ſeruant why he gaue as much to him that wrought but one hower, as to them that laboured many howers, alledged his will onely for a reaſon, <hi>Volo huic no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſsimo dare ſicut tibi: I vvill giue vnto this laſt as vnto thee,</hi> verſ. 14. and againe verſ. 15. <hi>Is it not lawfull for me to do what I will?</hi> and it is ſaid of God the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.</note> 1. Cor. 12. that one and the ſame ſpirit worketh the varietie of ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations which are mentioned in that chapter, deuiding to euery one <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>euen as he vvill;</hi> whereupon <hi>Caietan</hi> notes, <hi>voluntas ſpiritus ſancti pro ratione redditur:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caiet. ibid.</note> The will of the holy Ghoſt is alledged for a ſufficient reaſon of his action; and in that his will is alledged for a reaſon of his action, it is apparent, ſaith he, and a ſufficient argument that he is a true God.</p>
            <p>Now what might be the cauſe why our Sauiour being God, and equal to the Father and the holy Ghoſt in deitie, would not haue his will only ſtand for a reaſon, and when the great Lords and mightie Potentates of the world ſay <hi>ſic volo, ſic facio, ſtet pro ratione voluntas,</hi> would render a reaſon of this his action? was it becauſe he had to deale with men who were docile, and reaſonable, and of good capacitie, and not with wilfull and ſtubborne men? For <hi>Theophilact</hi> hath this kinde of rule, <hi>Solere Deum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theophil. in epiſt. ad Rom.</note> 
               <hi>cum agit cum hominibus non malignis, &amp; querulis, factorum ſuorum reddere rationem,</hi> That it is the cuſtome of God when he deales with men that are reaſonable and tractable, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a reaſon of his actions why he doth them: <hi>Cum autem agit cum malignis, &amp; querulis, ſuam ſolùm allegare volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem:</hi> but when he hath to do with obſtinate and malicious men, to alledge onely his will for a reaſon, becauſe they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21754:6"/>
are not worthy to haue other reaſon giuen them, of which his rule he alledgeth many examples.</p>
            <p>I cannot define this to be the reaſon, but it is not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether improbable; for to graunt that both the Scribes and Phariſes and the Prieſts too were obſtinate and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious: yet (though they were very many of them) they were a ſmall number being compared with them who were then preſent when this action was done; for it may be collected probably out of the Goſpell, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour had moſt commonly attending vpon him to heare his doctrine and ſee his miracles, eight or ten thouſand people: for he had in the deſart one time 5000. another time 4000.<note place="margin">Orig. cont. Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum lib. <hi>2.</hi> Euſeb. lib. <hi>3.</hi> ca. <hi>6.</hi> de de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſt. euang.</note> beſides women and children: and this num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber is noted by <hi>Origen contra Celſum lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 6. <hi>de demonſt. euang.</hi> For if he had ſo many in the deſart places where they could haue no ſuſtenance, what companies may be imagined did follow,<note place="margin">Luc. 8.</note> when he went <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, through ſo many cities and villages the moſt populous of all the world?<note place="margin">Ioſeph. de bel. Iud. li. <hi>3.</hi> ca. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> For <hi>Ioſephus</hi> notes that in Galile there were 400. townes (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Euangeliſt calles the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>oppida ſine muris,</hi> as <hi>Euthinius</hi> notes in the firſt of Math) in euery of which townes there were at leaſt 15000. inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as the ſame <hi>Ioſephus</hi> notes: and their cities were proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to their townes, for in the land of Genezareth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many other famous cities, there was one called <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richaea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſeph. de bel. Iud. li. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occaſion ſerued would ſend out 40000. fighting men, and another called <hi>Tiberias,</hi> in which there were 600. Aldermen or Senators, as the ſame <hi>Ioſephus</hi> notes: by which proportions we may conceiue how po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous they were.</p>
            <p>But this ordinary number of followers, of 4000. or 5000. or 10000. was nothing to the multitude of people which were gathered together at this feaſt of the Paſſeouer, from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21754:6"/>
all the countries of Iudaea, and in likelyhood were preſent at this miracle. For <hi>Ceſtius Gallus</hi> the Preſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Syria,<note place="margin">Ioſeph. de bel. Iud. li. <hi>7.</hi> ca. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taken a view of them, and conſidered how many ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices were offered, and how many men went together to the eating of their part in theſe ſacrifices, informed <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> the Emperour, that the number of men then preſent was 2700000. at the leaſt, which all were counted holy and pure; for lepers and many other diſeaſed were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by the lawe, and all thoſe within the precinct of the temple: which number wil not ſeeme ſtrange to them that conſider the circuit of the temple and the courts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, and that all the Iewes from all parts of the world at that time aſſembled thither.</p>
            <p>Now to admit that the Scribes &amp; Phariſes and Prieſts, &amp;c. were ſtubborne and obſtinate, and therefore accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Theophil.</hi> rule deſerued not, that God ſhould giue them a reaſon of his action: yet the number of the people aſſembled being almoſt infinite in compariſon of them, who loued him ſo that in reſpect of them the Phariſes <hi>fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to offer him vvrong,</hi> Math. 26.<note place="margin">Math. 26.</note> 
               <hi>vvho hung vpon him to heare him,</hi> Luke. 19. <hi>pendebat velut inhians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Caiet.</hi> finally <hi>reioyſed, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in all the glorious things that were vvrought by him,</hi> Luke 13.<note place="margin">Luc. 13.</note> it is not abſurd to imagin that in reſpect of them our Sauiour vouchſafed to alledge this reaſon. Or was it becauſe, hauing ſhewed himſelfe more then a man to this great aſſembly by this miraculous action, ſo he would confirme this opinion by a miraculous ſpeech? For as <hi>igneum &amp; ſidereum quiddam radiabat in oculis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierome.</note> ſome fierie and ſtarrie brightneſſe gliſtered in his eyes when he wrought this action: ſo it could not be, but that his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie ſhould bewray it ſelfe in his ſpeech; firſt, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the matter, becauſe being not bred vp in learning to reade the ſcriptures, nor any accuſtomed auditor to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21754:7"/>
Scribes, for the gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maticall ſence, nor to the Phariſes for the miſtical ſence of the ſcriptures, he could neuertheleſſe properly, and to the preſent purpoſe alledge vnto them the ſayings of the Prophets. Secondly, concerning the manner of his ſpeech, which was extraordinary, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Luc. 4.</note> 
               <hi>his ſpeech vvas vvith authoritie and povver,</hi> not like the ſpeech of other men,<note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> of other learned men, the Scribes or the Phariſes, Math. 7. whoſe kinde of teaching was <hi>frigida,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iauſen. concord. cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; ad commouendum parum efficax: colde, and not effectual to moue;</hi> where as our Sauiours was full of force &amp; efficacie, mouing the hearts of the auditors to faith and repentance: it is not improbable to be for this cauſe.</p>
            <p>Or was it becauſe, ſeeing the Scribes and Phariſes did moſt eſpecially aſſault him, and ſeeke to confound him with queſtions and interrogations vpon the chiefe feaſts, when the people were aſſembled together,<note place="margin">Ioh. 7. Ioh. 10. Ioh. 5.</note> as in the feaſt of Tabernacles Ioh. 7. in the feaſt of the dedication of the Temple, Ioh. 10. in the feaſt of Pentecoſt, Ioh. 5. (for ſo <hi>S. Chryſoſtom, Cyrill,</hi> and <hi>Theophil.</hi> interpret it though it be not named) he would alſo in this great ſolemne feaſt and aſſembly at Eaſter, or the Paſſeouer, try how they could defend that abuſe of the temple, which he proued out of the prophets to be againſt the end &amp; the inſtitution of it? Whereunto whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they made no anſwere, he replied no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Greg. Moral.</hi> 23.9.</note> for <hi>Finis eſſe locutionis ſapientium ſolet, vt eouſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dicant quò aduerſarijs ſilentium imponant: The end of a vviſemans ſpeech is by good reaſon to put his aduerſaries to ſilence, and then vrge them no farther. Non enim ſe oſtendere, ſed praua docentes compeſcere ſtudent: For they ſpeake not to oſtentation but to confute or confound them that teach or do amiſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or was it done for our inſtruction? as euery action of his is ſome inſtruction for vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thom.</hi> 12. <hi>q.</hi> 71. <hi>ar.</hi> 6.</note> to teach vs to do nothing raſhly, heddely, and without conſideration, as great Lords
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21754:7"/>
and Tyrants do, the rule of whoſe actions is their wil, their froward and obſtinate will: but to meaſure all our ſayings and doings with <hi>humane reaſon,</hi> which is <hi>regula propinqua, &amp; homogenea,</hi> as the Scholemen call it, a rule which is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, bred within vs, neere vnto vs, in our mouthes, and in our harts,<note place="margin">Deut. 30.14.</note> or with the <hi>vvord of God</hi> which is <hi>regula re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mota &amp; heterogenea,</hi> a rule hid from vs, farre off from vs, in heauen, in the boſome of God, <hi>quaſi ratio Dei,</hi> but yet made knowen vnto vs by the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Which rule and inſtruction the holy Fathers and men of God haue euer obſerued,<note place="margin">Greg. Hom. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> confirming their doctrine with reaſon and authoritie, <hi>Nos affirmare nolumus quod a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertis teſtimonijs no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> approbamus: vve vvill affirme nothing but vvhat vve can proue by reaſon and authoritie;</hi> and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting themſelues and their iudgements to reaſon and authoritie: <hi>Arguant me ratione velauthoritate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Policra. prolog. lib. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; ego vel ad inimici vocem no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> refugie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> emendari: Let it be grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded on rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or authoritie, &amp; I wil giue eare to the reproofe of an enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this patterne of our Sauiour not only priuat men, but the whole Church of Chriſt in their lawes and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions do redily imitate: <hi>Sancta eccleſia ex magiſterio hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militatis inſtituta, The holy Church bred vp in the ſchoole of humilitie, and following the ſteps of our maiſter Chriſt,<note place="margin">Greg. moral. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> Recta quae errant bus dicit, non quaſi ex authoritate praecipit, ſed ex ratione perſuadet: Force not men to beleeue that which is true by authoritie, but perſwade them by reaſon:</hi> becauſe as it is wiſely obſerued, <hi>Plus mouere ſolet ratio inſerta in mandato,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Humbert. in regulam Aug.</note> 
               <hi>quàm ipſum mandatum,</hi> a reaſon inſerted to a lawe or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, moues much more then a naked lawe: And therefore the Church ſaith with Iob, <hi>videte an mentiar, Examine whether I ly or no:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 6.</note> beleeue not that which I ſay becauſe I ſpeake it: <hi>ſed an vera ſint ex ratione penſate,</hi> but weigh with reaſon the truth of it: and if the Church do
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21754:8"/>
teach that (as oftentimes it doth) which cannot be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended within the compaſſe of reaſon; yet for all that, <hi>rationabiliter ſuadet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>it perſwades you with reaſon, Ne de oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultis ratio humana quaeri debeat, That of ſome myſteries and ſecrets of Chriſtianitie, you may not aske or ſeeke the reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas on the other part it is the cuſtome and order of ſtubborne men, of hereticks, &amp; ſchiſmaticks, <hi>Non rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones afferre, ſed placita:</hi> not to vrge reaſon, but their will, their pleaſure,<note place="margin">Aug. contra Fauſtum Man. lib. <hi>14.</hi> ca. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> their phantaſie, or opinion: as <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the <hi>Manichee,</hi> when he had charged <hi>Moyſes</hi> that he did <hi>diuina laceſſere, offer viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the lawes of God; dixit, &amp; abijt,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Auſtine, nihil probare ſategit, nihil curauit ostendere:</hi> he ſaid, as <hi>Pilate</hi> ſaid, <hi>quod ſcripſi, ſcripſi, quod dixi, dixi:</hi> when he had ſaid it, he had done, he neuer made offer to proue it, or giue a reaſon of his ſpeech: and though our doctrine be neuer ſo true, yet it is without the compaſſe of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and diſcretion for any man be he neuer ſo learned, to vſe theſe kinds of aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: <hi>Ego in hoc libro non contuli: ſed aſſerui &amp; aſſero, &amp; penes nullum volo eſſe iudicium, ſed omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſuadeo, vt praestent obſequium,</hi> I haue not vſed proofes, or authoritie in my writing; but I affirme that that I ſay, and ſubmit my ſelfe to no mans iudgement, but require e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man to conſent to me: <hi>ſcio me mea dogmata habere de caelo:</hi> I know that my ſpeeches deſcend from heauen, are authenticall and canonicall; for it is a propertie peculiar to God only,<note place="margin">Caiet. ſuper <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>facere prout vult,</hi> to do what he liſt, and ſay what he pleaſeth: for other men muſt haue <hi>regulam vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatis,</hi> a rule to direct their will, and ſome reaſon to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect their ſpeach; otherwiſe while he takes vpon him a propertie or qualitie peculiar to God, he becomes <hi>fatuus confidens in ſtultitia ſua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 17.</note> 
               <hi>a foole that is confident in his owne follie.</hi> And thus much by way of probabilitie, why our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour would alledge a reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21754:8"/>The Preface to this ſpeech of his, is this, <hi>Scriptum eſt,</hi> it is written. I noted before vnto you, that we muſt vſe ſome rule wherby to ſquare out and meaſure our ſpeeches and actions, and one was from within vs, <hi>homogenea re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula,</hi> mans reaſon: another from without vs, <hi>regula hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genea,</hi> Gods word: he vſeth this ſecond rule as the ſureſt rule, which cannot erre; the word of God; which rule, though it be <hi>heterogenea,</hi> ſupernaturall to vs, yet it is <hi>homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genea,</hi> naturall to him, who was God himſelfe, for the word of God may be ſaid to be <hi>ratio Dei,</hi> which was <hi>homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genea</hi> to him, as humane reaſon is to man. So that his ſpeech is not a bare reaſon, which peraduenture might ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit cauils, and exceptions, and contradictions, but is ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with authoritie, as good authoritie as any Prophet ſpake with when he ſaid, <hi>Haec dicit dominus</hi> thus ſayth the Lord: And this <hi>S. Auſtine</hi> ſaith, is <hi>or do naturae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de mor. eccle. catho. ca. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the order of nature,</hi> that when we learne any thing, or teach any thing, eſpecially touching faith and religion, <hi>Rationem praecedat authoritas, Reaſon ſhould be grounded vpon ſome good autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie:</hi> for ſaith he, <hi>Infirma ratio videri poteſt quae cum red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita fuerit, authoritatem poſtea per quam firmetur aſſumat: For it may ſeeme to be a vveake reaſon, vvhich vvhen it is alledged requireth ſome other reaſon and authoritie to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it.</hi> Now our Sauiours reaſon was grounded vpon good authoritie, vpon that which was <hi>regula prima, the chiefe rule</hi> with the Iewes, eſpecially Scribes and Phariſes and Prieſts, which is, the <hi>vvritten vvord of God,</hi> which being deliuered ſincerely according to the true ſence and meaning of it, as he did, admits no deniall; and therefore the Phariſes do make no reply.</p>
            <p>Now it is worth the obſeruation to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider our Sauiours manner of reaſoning with them; It is moſt certaine that with all ſorts of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that confeſſe there is a God, the word,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21754:9"/>
and will of God, is <hi>regula prima,</hi> the firſt and the chiefeſt rule to direct them in all their actions: and therfore ſome heathen haue the ſpeeches of oracles for their chiefe rule, <hi>fruitur<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> deorum colloquio:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virg. Aenei. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> other the word of God, which is <hi>ſcriptum in cordibus,</hi> written in our hearts, naturall reaſon for their chiefe rule, as the Philoſophers had: other the word of God written by the pen of man, but inſpired by the holy Ghoſt, as the Iewes had the old Teſtament for their chiefe rule, and Chriſtians both the old and the new: and whoſoeuer diſputed with any one of theſe ſorts of men, out of theſe grounds which they receiued for their chiefe rule, diſputed demonſtratiuely, and otherwiſe not ſo: for a reaſon or authoritie from the ſcripture will not moue a Philoſopher, nor a reaſon from the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is no rule for a Iewe. Wherefore our Sauiour hauing to deale with the Scribes and Phariſes and Prieſts, &amp;c. who receiued the word of God written in bookes of the law and the Prophets for their chiefe rule, he diſputed with them out of the law and the Prophets, and in this place drawes his reaſon from the prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> and the prophet <hi>Ieremy:</hi> and in the next chapter diſputing with the Saduces about the reſurrection,<note place="margin">Math. 22.</note> which receiued only the fiue bookes of <hi>Moyſes</hi> for the written word of God, and their chiefe rule, he alledgeth his reaſons from the bookes of <hi>Moyſes</hi> only. Which example the Apoſtles and holy Fathers haue fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in all their diſcourſes: for <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſpeaking to the Athenians before their conuerſion, alledgeth no text of ſcripture, but reaſons drawen from the light of nature, which was their chiefe rule, and the ſaying of their Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher,<note place="margin">Act. 17.</note> Act. 17. And preaching to the Corinthians after their conuerſion, alledgeth the ſcripture as <hi>regula prima,</hi> or <hi>remota</hi> with Chriſtians: and the reaſons or ſayings of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> as <hi>regula propinqua,</hi> the rule of naturall and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21754:9"/>
men; which courſe alſo is now obſerued in our preaching.<note place="margin">Aug. de mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus cul. catho. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>S. Auſtine</hi> diſputing with the Manichees which denyed the old Teſtament to be the word of God, brought his proofes and reaſons from the new Teſtament only, becauſe they allowed that for their onely rule: and therefore <hi>Lactantius</hi> taketh exception againſt that maner of diſputation which <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> vſed with <hi>Demetrian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lact. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> who vrged him too much with authorities of ſcripture, ſeeing <hi>Demetrian</hi> allowed not the ſcripture for his rule: <hi>Non enim Scripturae teſtimonijs, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ille vanam, fictam, commentitiam putabat, ſed argumentis &amp; ratione fuerat refellendus: For he was to be reproued and conuinced with arguments and reaſon, not with the ſcripture, which he eſteemed as falſe, fained, and counterfeite,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lactantius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But our Sauiours manner of diſputation <hi>ſcriptum eſt,</hi> it is written, in the lawe or in the prophets, is demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue with Iewes or Chriſtians, who accept the ſcripture for their chiefe rule: But for aſmuch as not the letter of the ſcripture is the word of God, but the true ſence, and meaning of it, you (beloued Chriſtians) are eſpecially to regard who it is that deliuereth or alledgeth this ſcripture to you; for although <hi>in veritate humana, in humane truth,</hi> (where reaſon only is a ſufficient rule, and principle, which is true of neceſſitie, whether a poore man or a rich man, a learned man, or an ignorant man, a Chriſtian or an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, Baalam or his Aſſe, deliuer it) we muſt rather conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>quid dicatur, quam quis loquatur,</hi> what is ſaid, then who ſaith it; yet <hi>in veritate diuina, in diuine truth,</hi> which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mans reaſon, and is beleeued becauſe it is ſo deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the ſcripture, which we accept for the word of God, becauſe we cannot euer iudge, <hi>quid dicatur</hi> what is ſaid, we muſt eſpecially conſider <hi>quis loquatur,</hi> who ſaith it; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be the diuell which ſaith <hi>ſcriptum eſt,</hi> it is written,<note place="margin">Math. 4.</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:21754:10"/>
as he did to our Sauiour,<note place="margin">Math. 4.</note> or ſome Atheiſt, or ſome Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, or ſome Schiſmaticke, &amp;c. or whether it be our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt, or his true Church, or ſome found member of his Church.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de vtilit. Cred. cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note>For as <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quod aliquid intelligimus rationi, quod credimus authoritati debemus,</hi> Though we owe all things, both knowledge, and beliefe vnto God <hi>primariò,</hi> yet as to his meanes and inſtruments we are indebted to reaſon, for that that we know, and to authoritie, for that we beleeue.<note place="margin">Orig. Hom. <hi>31.</hi> in Luc.</note> And therefore <hi>S. Origen</hi> giues this obſeruable rule, <hi>Si quando teſtimonia de ſcriptura audieris, vide ne ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim loquenti acquieſcas, ſed conſidera illum cuius ſit, ac cuius ſententiae, cuius ſit voluntatis.</hi> When you heare one ſay <hi>ſcriptum eſt,</hi> it is written, beleeue him not therefore in that which he ſaith, but conſider who it is that ſpeaketh it, of what opinion he is, whether an hereticke or no, of what minde or affection he be, whether a ſchiſmaticke or no; for if he diſſemble that which he is not, and being infected with the poiſon of hereſie or ſchiſme, a wolfe do lurke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ſheepes skin; then the deuill in him ſaith <hi>ſcriptum eſt,</hi> the ſcriptures do nothing belong vnto him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aug. tract. <hi>18.</hi> ſuper Ioan.</note>For as hereſies haue their beginning by occaſion of ſcripture not well vnderſtoode, <hi>Quia ſcripturae bonae intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liguntur non benè,</hi> as <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> ſaith, ſo the practiſe of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks is <hi>per verba legis legem impugnare,</hi> by the words of ſcripture to ouerthrow the ſcripture,<note place="margin">Ambroſ. ſuper <hi>3.</hi> ad Tit.</note> 
               <hi>Ambr. ſuper</hi> 3. <hi>ad Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp; proprium ſenſum verbis aſtruere legis,</hi> to build their own opinions vpon the words or text of the law. And this verball alledging of the ſcripture is that ſheepes skin wherewith wolues be clothed, ſaith <hi>Vincent. Lirin. Quid eſt veſtitus ouium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vincent. Lirin. cap. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>niſi prophetarum &amp; apoſtolorum proloquia?</hi> What is the ſheepes clothing but the ſayings of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles? and, <hi>Qui ſunt lupi rapaces, niſi ſenſus
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21754:10"/>
haereticorum feri &amp; rabidi,</hi> and what be theſe rauening wolues, but the wilde and vnnaturall interpretations of hereticks? And when our Sauiour charged the Saduces <hi>that they erred, not knowing the ſcriptures,</hi> it was not that they were ignorant of the letter of the ſcripture, at leaſt of ſo much as they acknowledged for ſcripture, but becauſe they knew not the ſenſe, and meaning of it:<note place="margin">Ioſeph. Antiq. lib. <hi>13.</hi> cap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> for <hi>Ioſephus</hi> ſaith of them, that they read the ſcriptures, and the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures only, and reiected all manner Phariſaicall traditions.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ſeeing many ſay, It is written, with our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, and yet neuertheleſſe are deceiued themſelues, and deceiue others, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Math. 22.</note> 
               <hi>not knowing the ſenſe of them,</hi> as the Saduces were: and others <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, do mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly wreſt them,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.</note> as <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſaith ſome did <hi>S. Paules</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to their owne deſtruction, and to the deſtruction of other their auditors and followers:</hi> though there be nothing ſo certaine and authenticall as the holy ſcriptures, if we be ſure <hi>quid dicatur,</hi> what is the true ſenſe and meaning of them, yet there is nothing ſo dangerous, if being not able to iudge our ſelues, we do not conſider <hi>quis loquatur,</hi> who it is that doth alledge them. But now let vs conſider what that is which our Sauiour ſaith is written in the ſcriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My houſe ſhall be called the houſe of prayer, but you haue made it a denne of theeues.</hi> The words of <hi>Eſay</hi> implie, whoſe houſe this Temple was, Gods houſe: and ſecondly, the end or vſe, why it was built, to pray in. The words of <hi>Ieremy</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie the abuſe of it, that of Gods houſe, it was become an houſe for theeues: and where it was ordained to pray in, they had made it a denne to lurke in, and ſo ſafely to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any robbery, or ſacriledge.</p>
            <p>It is moſt certaine, that God who is the Lord and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of all things, hath reſerued to himſelfe a part or por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21754:11"/>
in all things, not that he hath neede of them, but in <hi>recognitionem,</hi> that all things that are haue proceeded from him: and that he is the moſt high and abſolute Lord ouer them all: and therefore though he be king of kings, and Lord of lords, and ſo by conſequent of all people and nations in the world, yet he hath reſerued an eſpeciall por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men to himſelf, which he calleth <hi>his people:</hi> though he be infinite, and comprehended in no place, yet he will haue ſome particular place whither this his people may reſort to ſerue him, which he calleth <hi>his houſe,</hi> his place, his habitation:<note place="margin">Dan. 7.10.</note> though thouſands of angels miniſter vnto him, and ten thouſand thouſand ſtand before him, yet he hath among men alſo appointed ſome to his proper ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in this his houſe,<note place="margin">Numb. 3.11.</note> and thoſe he calles <hi>his Prieſts, his Miniſters:</hi> though he be a ſpirit, and hath no neede of theſe corporall things, yet he challengeth a part or por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in all things for the furniſhing of this his houſe, and maintenance of theſe his ſeruants: which he calleth his part, his portion, his tithes, his offerings: though he be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, and before all times, yet he hath reſerued ſome times &amp; ſome dayes as proper to him, wherein his people ſhould reſort to his houſe to ſerue him, which he calleth his feaſts, his Sabbothes. Heere mention is made of his houſe only, and therefore of that I will frame my ſpeech, and ſome certaine circumſtances belonging vnto it.</p>
            <p>It is moſt manifeſt that God who is comprehended in no place, hath had notwithſtanding ſome place alotted to him euer ſince the beginning of the world, and therefore ſome very learned men haue affirmed, that <hi>Adam</hi> euen in Paradiſe had a certaine place where to preſent himſelfe before the Lord, that place where God walked and called him to him,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.8. Gen. 4.3.4.</note> Gen. 3.8. and certaine Hebrew interpreters conclude out of the 4. of Gen. ver. 3.4. that <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Abell</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21754:11"/>
did bring their ſacrifices, <hi>adduxerunt ſacrificia ſua</hi> (for ſo the word imports) to their father <hi>Adam,</hi> who was then the Prieſt, that he might offer them in the place which the Lord appointed for that purpoſe. In that place where God appeared vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> becauſe that place was holy there he built an altar, Gen. 12. ver. 7.<note place="margin">Gen. 12.7.</note> And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded <hi>Abraham</hi> to offer his ſonne <hi>Iſaak,</hi> he appointed him the place where it ſhould be done, on a mountaine; and there <hi>Abraham</hi> built an altar alſo, Gen. 22.<note place="margin">Gen. 22.</note> and this was the place where afterward the temple of <hi>Salomon</hi> was built, 2. Chro. 3. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Rebecka</hi> felt the children ſtriue,<note place="margin">2. Chro. 3. Gen. 25.22.</note> ſhe went to aske the Lord; no doubt to ſome place where he vſed to giue them anſwere; the interlineall gloſſe ſaith, to the place where <hi>Abraham</hi> built his altar. <hi>Iacob</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the diuers places he dwelt in, had diuers places to ſerue God in, and there erected diuers altars; and the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion that God tooke to deliuer the children of Iſraell out of the Aegyptian bondage, was, that they might go to a certaine place to ſerue him, and offer ſacrifice to him: <hi>we pray thee let them go three dayes iourney in the deſert there to ſacrifice vnto God,</hi> ſaid <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> vnto <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> Exod. 5.<note place="margin">Exod. 5.</note> and the place which God appointed was mount Sinai, Exo. 19. In the deſart there was a tabernacle, which <hi>Lira</hi> calleth <hi>tabernaculum paruum, the little tabernacle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 19.</note> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lira ſuper Exod.</hi> 16. Exod. 33.</note> in compariſon of the great tabernacle, Exod. 33. whither <hi>Aaron</hi> commaunded the people to come into the preſence of the Lord,<note place="margin">Exod. 16.9.</note> Exo. 16.9. and whither <hi>Moyſes</hi> brought <hi>Iethro</hi> to heare all the wonders which God had done for them, and to offer ſacrifice vnto God,<note place="margin">Exod. 18. Exod. 26.</note> Exod. 18. In the 26. of Exod. charge was giuen to make that great tabernacle, a moueable tabernacle, which ſhould continue for the houſe of God, till they had ſome ſetled habitation: finally when their eſtate was ſetled, God choſe Ieruſalem for the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21754:12"/>
place, and in Ieruſalem mount Moriah, to build this temple in, this houſe of God, which heere is mentioned.</p>
            <p>All theſe places howſoeuer otherwiſe called, were yet <hi>domus dei, Gods houſes,</hi> bicauſe there eſpecially he affoorded his preſence: And therefore when <hi>Caine</hi> ſtoode (as I may ſay) excommunicated, for murdering his brother, and might not come into the place appointed for the ſeruice of God, he was ſaid to be <hi>fugatus à praeſentia domini,</hi> caſt out from the preſence of the Lord,<note place="margin">Gen. 4. Ionas. 1.3.</note> Gen. 4. and when <hi>Ionas</hi> was ſaid <hi>to haue fled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the preſence of the Lord, Aben Ezra</hi> ſaith that he fled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that place, where the Prophets ſtoode, and offered themſelues to be ſent of God, when he ſhould commaund them: and when it is ſaid that <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> died before the Lord, it is meant that they died before the altar of the Lord, Numb. 3.4. and when any thing was ſaid to be done before the Arke,<note place="margin">Ioſua. 24. 1. Sam. 21.</note> as Ioſua 24. or before the tabernacle 1. Sam. 21. or in the temple, it was ſaid to be done <hi>coram domino,</hi> or <hi>ad dominum, before the Lord, or in the preſence of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as before the law and vnder the law God had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his peculiar, and proper places to be worſhipped in, which therefore were called by his name, Gods Temple, Gods tabernacle, Gods houſe: ſo after the law and vnder the Goſpell, aſſoone as euer Kings and Queenes became nurſes of Chriſtianitie, and profeſſors of religion, there were peculiar places conſecrated to the ſeruice of God, which now alſo are called Gods houſes, <hi>domus Dei,</hi> both becauſe they are conſecrated to him, and becauſe there we performe holy and diuine miniſteries to him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that place being accepted of him for the place of his preſence and habitation amongſt men, <hi>plus perticipat ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationis &amp; gratiae Dei. Damaſ. Orth. fid. lib.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Damaſ. orth. fid. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>cap.</hi> 16. and in them doth diſpenſe vnto vs by his holy myſteries his mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21754:12"/>
bleſſings. And as thoſe houſes, and eſpecially that houſe we here ſpeake of was renowmed aboue the palaces of the greateſt Princes, for a double furniture; a liuing furniture, and a dead furniture; that is, with multitudes of people, and with rich, and ſumptuous ornaments, great treaſures and large reuenewes; and therfore found two ſorts of enemies, one that would rob it of the people; another that would ſpoile it of the riches and reuennewes: ſo the houſe of God vnder Chriſtianitie, hath excelled <hi>magnitudine &amp; pulchritudine aedificiorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſ. Hom. <hi>66,</hi> ad pop. Ant.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; quod maius est conuenientium studio:</hi> that is, hath thoſe two kinde of fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitures and thoſe two kindes of enemies, which do rob it of the one and the other.</p>
            <p>That great ſchiſmaticke <hi>Ieroboam</hi> made a ſchiſme or rente in the church of God,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 12.</note> that ſo he might continue the rent or ſchiſme which he made in the kingdome; and the meanes which he vſed to make this rente, was to prohibite ten tribes of the twelue to goe vp, and doe ſacrifice in the houſe of the Lord, 3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 12. which were bound by the law to ſhewe themſelues certaine times in the yeere at this houſe of God which was at Ieruſalem: and the ſpeeche which he made to perſwade them was this: <hi>Viri populares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſeph. Antiqu lib. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>notum vobis existimo, quod nullus locus Deo est vacuus, &amp; quod is nullo certo loco includitur, ſed vbique vota exaudit, vbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que cultores ſuos reſpicit, &amp;c.</hi> My good people and friendes ſaith he, I doubt not but you know, that no place is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God, &amp; that no place doth containe God, but where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we pray he can heare vs, and whereſoeuer we ſerue him he can ſee vs, &amp;c. and by theſe and like ſpeeches with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew the people from the ſeruice of God in his houſe at Ieruſalem, and builded altars which ſerued for idolatrie, and robbed the church of this firſt kinde of furniture.</p>
            <p>Thus alſo many ſchiſmaticks and heretikes, and ſuch
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21754:13"/>
politicians as <hi>Ieroboam</hi> was, ſince the comming of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt hath endeuoured to rob his churches, of this ſpeciall ornament of the multitude of people (for the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of the people is the glorie of the King Prouerbs 14.<note place="margin">Prou. 14.</note> (that is <hi>gloria Christi</hi> ſaith the interlineall gloſſe) either to make rents and rebellions in kingdomes or ſchiſmes and deuiſions in the houſe of God. Of theſe politicians this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter age hath too much experience:<note place="margin">
                  <p>Damaſ. haereſ. <hi>80.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Concil. Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grenſ. circa an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num <hi>328.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> and <hi>Damaſcen</hi> telleth vs of <hi>Maſsilians</hi> which to other hereſies did adde <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorum contemptum,</hi> the contempt of Churches: and in <hi>Gangrenſi Concilio</hi> there is mention made of one <hi>Euſtathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Templa Dei nullius est vtilitatis,</hi> that there was no vſe of Churches, and the <hi>Petrobruſiani</hi> laughed and ſcoffed at Churches: and others there were called <hi>Pſeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do-apostoli,</hi> who affirmed <hi>Eccleſiam non plus valere ad oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, quam ſtabulum porcorum,</hi> that a church was of no more vſe for prayer, then a ſtable or hogſtie: As alſo many in theſe dayes who accompt of them but as of temples of <hi>Baal,</hi> and ſynagogues of Idolatrie: vſing the ſame reaſons that <hi>Ieroboam</hi> did, and ſome texts of ſcriptures, miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode, or not well applied: and thus woulde robbe the Church of God, of the beſt kinde of furniture, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne and inlarge their owne priuate conuenticles.</p>
            <p>For that other kind of furniture it is moſt certaine that as no Church or Temple was renowmed more for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing furniture, for the multitudes of people that reſorted thither; ſo no Church in the world was more renowmed for the ornaments, riches and reuenewes that belonged to it: for although God be a ſpirit, yet he will not be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped in ſpirit onely; but in bodie alſo, <hi>glorifie God in bodie &amp; in ſpirit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.</note> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. and the reaſon that he alleadgeth is this onely, <hi>for they are his:</hi> Now if this be a good reaſon why we ſhould honor God, who is a ſpirit, both with ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21754:13"/>
and bodie becauſe <hi>they be his,</hi> by the ſame reaſon we muſt honor God, with our time, with our richeſſe and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, for <hi>they alſo are his.</hi> And that reaſon which Saint <hi>Paule</hi> vſeth vnder the Goſpell why we ſhould honor God with our body; the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> vnder the lawe vſed why he would honor him with his ſubſtance: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vſeth this reaſon of his great gift toward the building and furniſhing of the Temple: <hi>for all things come of thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Chro. 29.14</note> 1. Chro. 29.14.</p>
            <p>Now as there was neuer any nation that acknowledged a God, which did not honor him in their Temples, with ſome part of their beſt riches and ſubſtance: ſo eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the people of God, aſſoone as they had a certaine place, though mooueable, as was the tabernacle; or a place certaine vnmooueable as was this Temple, they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vp to him, as a ſigne that they held of him <hi>in capite,</hi> ſome good part of their beſt riches, and iewels, to adorne his houſe withall: to the making and furniſhing of the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle they brought gold, ſiluer, braſſe, blew ſilk, purple, ſcarlet, fine linnen, goates haire, rich skins, Schittim wood, oyle, ſpices, Onyx ſtones, and ſtones for the Ephod.<note place="margin">Exod. 25. &amp; 35</note> And leaſt you ſhould thinke it to proceed from a kind of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition or ſuperfluitie, you ſhall vnderſtand that it was done by the commandement of God; for <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſaith to the congregation that <hi>God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded an offering to be taken from amongſt you vnto the Lord,</hi> Exod. 35.4.<note place="margin">Exod. 35.4.</note> &amp; yet leaſt you ſhould thinke it not done of deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but of neceſſity, none might giue but he that was <hi>vltroneus,</hi> Exod. 25.<note place="margin">Exod. 25. Exod. 35.</note> 
               <hi>volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tarius &amp; pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pti animi,</hi> Exo. 35. <hi>he that was of a free &amp; willing hart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the making and furniſhing of the Temple, K. <hi>Dauid</hi> gaue of his owne, 3000. talents of gold,<note place="margin">1. Chro. 29.4.</note> and 7000. talents ſiluer, beſides braſſe, iron, wood, Onyx ſtones, &amp; Carbun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle ſtones of diuers colour, and all pretious ſtones, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21754:14"/>
marble, in great abundance: and perſwaded them that were of abilitie to do thereafter; ſo that the Princes of the families beſides all other neceſſaries gaue 5000. talents of gold, and 10000. talents of ſiluer, and 18000. talents of braſſe,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> &amp; an hundred thouſand talents of iron, &amp;c. beſides all that which <hi>Solomon</hi> prouided. And as the tabernacle was made by the commaundement by God, ſo was this Temple; for <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, that he had the <hi>frame of it, and the patterne ſent to him by writing by the hand of the Lord.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">1. Chro. 28.19.</note> Chro. 28.19. and both <hi>Dauid</hi> and his people <hi>offered their gifts willingly and with a perfit hart and with reioycing Ibid. cap.</hi> 29. as did they that made the tabernacle.<note place="margin">Ibid. cap. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> The like might be ſaid of the ſecond temple if the time would ſerue.</p>
            <p>Now that you may knowe how acceptable vnto God this kinde of ſeruice is, of building his houſes and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing them in moſt ſumptuous manner; you ſhall obſerue, (and it woorth the obſeruing) that after <hi>Dauid</hi> had deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined with himſelfe to build the Temple, and not before, God promiſed to eſtabliſh the kingdome to his ſeed. 2. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel.</hi> 7.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 7. Pſal. 132.</note> which <hi>Dauid</hi> ſeemeth alſo to note himſelfe in the Pſal. where after he had me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned his loue to Gods houſe, he noteth the loue of God to his houſe, &amp; his promiſe <hi>to ſet the fruit of his body vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his throne:</hi> Secondly, although <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> had many ſonnes,<note place="margin">2. Reg. 3. 1. Chro. 3.</note> which are named in the 2. Reg. 3. <hi>Amnon, Chileab, Abſolon, Adoniah, Shephatiah, Ithream:</hi> yet to none of theſe was the kingdome promiſed after him, but to <hi>Solomon</hi> who was borne after his good intent of building Gods houſe. Thirdly, though God promiſed many bleſſings to <hi>Solomon</hi> when he craued wiſedome, as richeſſe, glory, long life, &amp;c. yet he neuer promiſed that his ſeede ſhould raigne after him till ſuch time as he had fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the houſe of God.<note place="margin">1. Reg. 9.</note> 1. Reg. 9. but then he ſaid, <hi>thou ſhalt not want a man vpon the throwen of Iſrael.</hi> Fourthly, when
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21754:14"/>
the Temple was reedified by <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and others in moſt ſumptuous manner,<note place="margin">Zach. 6.</note> God commanded two crownes to be made <hi>Zach.</hi> 6. with the names of the chiefe benefactors engraued in them, and cauſed them to be placed in the Temple, for a perpetuall memory and moſt honorable te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony to all poſterity of their zeale &amp; liberalitie towards the houſe of God.</p>
            <p>And this kinde of furniture was not proper to Gods houſe vnder the law onely, but likewiſe vnder the goſpell; for as <hi>Eſayas</hi> propheſie was fulfilled vnder chriſtianity, <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus meae, domus orationis vocabitur cunctis gentibus;</hi> that Gods houſe ſhould be the houſe of praier to all nations,<note place="margin">Eſay. 56.</note> and the houſe of praier ſhould be likewiſe Gods houſe: ſo it ſhould ſeem that <hi>Dauids</hi> wiſh or prayer reached euen to vs that were after the law, who deſired of God <hi>that he would keepe for euer this voluntarie bountie, and liberalitie in furniſhing Gods houſe, in the purpoſe and the thoughts of the harts of his people.</hi> And therefore aſſoone as God gaue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe to his Church, oratories were built; and aſſoone as God rayſed vp Kings and Princes which fauoured the Chriſtian truth and religion,<note place="margin">1. Chro. 29.18.</note> no coſt was ſpared to furniſh the Churches, which alſo were builded with royall mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence: Al which the ancient fathers of the Church the chiefe pillers and lights of the goſpell after the Apoſtles, iudged as acceptable vnto God, as the making and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of the tabernacle, or <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Euſebius</hi> noteth the great ioie which the Chriſtians conceiued when <hi>Constantine</hi> builte thoſe magnificent Churches and furniſhed them to be <hi>laetitia diuino munere infuſa,</hi> a ioy whereof God was the author,<note place="margin">Euſ. eccle. hiſt. lib. <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi> ex verſ. ruff. Cyril. chare. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> not proceeding from vanitie or ſuperſtition. <hi>Cyrillus</hi> Biſhop of Ieruſalem ſaieth that the Kings in his time did adorne the Churches with ſiluer and gold, &amp;c. <hi>pietatis ergô,</hi> in holynes and deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21754:15"/>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> calleth thoſe voluntary donations <hi>depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta pietatis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get.</note> pledges and teſtimonies of religion, pietie and deuotion.<note place="margin">Orat. <hi>1.</hi> contra Iulian.</note> 
               <hi>Greg. Nazian.</hi> ſaieth, that the coſt which <hi>Gallus, Iulianus</hi> brother beſtowed vpon the Church which he built, <hi>was acceptable to God, euen as Abels ſacrifice.</hi> Saint <hi>August.</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Auguſt. ſuper Pſal. <hi>113.</hi> con. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> that the veſſels of golde and ſiluer which were vſed in the celebration of the ſacraments, were <hi>Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> holy, and conſecrated to his honor, <hi>cui pro ſalute nostra inde ſeruitur:</hi> And thus you ſee, that this houſe of God, both by Gods appointment, and to his great good liking, hath euer beene adorned with this rich furniture.</p>
            <p>But as there haue beene many ſorts of theeues and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, hereticks, ſchiſmaticks, and politicians, which would rob God of that liuing furniture of the multitude of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; ſo are there and euer haue beene many Atheiſtes and irreligious Iulianiſts, which haue beene readie to rifle his houſe of this other furniture, to ſpoile the Church of the ornaments and all other riches, landes, and reuenewes which were giuen vnto God to maintaine his houſe, and his houſhold withall: for it hath beene as true a rule in Gods houſe as in the dwellings of men, <hi>Difficilis magni custodia cenſus,</hi> where riches are theeues will reſort. Thus the firſt Temple builded by <hi>Salomon</hi> was deſtroyed by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bucodonozor,</hi> and the riches and furnitue carried to Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, and afterward fouly abuſed, and prophaned by <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tazar.</hi> The ſecond Temple being alſo admirable for the fabricke and the riches of it, though inferiour to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, was aſſaulted by <hi>Antiochus,</hi> by <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> by <hi>Pompey,</hi> by <hi>Craſsus,</hi> and ſome Roman Emperours: and of late yeeres in Chriſtianitie what ſo common as ſacriledge and robbing and ſpoyling of God in his houſe, and his houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold? ſo that where heretofore they complayned thus,
<q>
                  <l>Eccleſias Chriſti quas conſtruxere parentes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21754:15"/>Sternere nituntur nati pietate carentes:</l>
               </q>
They haue now brought their deſire to the iſſue, ſo that in countrey Villages <hi>Caneſcunt turpi templa relicta ſitu.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ouid.</note> The Churches are almoſt become that, which thoſe heretikes <hi>pſeudoa poſtoli</hi> likened them vnto, little better then hog-ſtyes; for the beſt preparation at any high feaſt is a little freſh ſtraw vnder their feete, the ordinary allowance for ſwine in their ſtye, or at the beſt <hi>Domus opportuna volucrum,</hi> (that which God threatned as a plague to Babylon) <hi>a cage of vncleane and hatefull birds:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 18.</note> and in cities and boroughes they are not like the Palaces of Princes as they were in the primitiue church, <hi>regijs aulis clariora,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chry. Hom. <hi>66.</hi> ad pop. Ant.</note> but like a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey hall, faire whitelimed, or a citizens parlour, at the beſt well wainſcotted; as though we were rather Platoniſts then Chriſtians, who would neither haue gold nor ſiluer in their churches becauſe it was <hi>Inuidioſa res,</hi> and gaue occaſion to ſacriledge; nor Iuorie that was taken from the bodie of a dead beaſt, becauſe that was <hi>Oblatio minimè ſancta,</hi> a prophane offering; nor iron nor braſſe, becauſe they were <hi>Inſtrumenta bellorum, inſtruments for warre:</hi> but <hi>Lapides &amp; ligna dicato qui velit, publiciſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> templis offerto:</hi> but if any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would dedicate wood or ſtones,<note place="margin">Theodor. ſerm. dedijs &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelis. ex Pla.</note> or ſuch baſe ſtuffe, it was lawful to do it: <hi>Theod.</hi> alledgeth it out of <hi>Plato.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the allowance which we make vnto God to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his family, is thin and bare, <hi>in quantum ſitis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iuuen. ſat. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, &amp; frigor a poſcunt:</hi> after the rate of a cup of cold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and a peece of bread, which ſhall be rewarded as our Sauiour ſaith at the day of iudgement, but to ſuch as are able to giue no more: after the rate of a frize coat, or a flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell waſtcote, which <hi>Dionyſius</hi> thought warme enough for winter, and cold enough for ſommer: after the rate of a Stoicks dinner, or Philoſophers breakfaſt: after the rate of <hi>Elias</hi> diet in the deſart, or <hi>Daniels</hi> in the Lions denne.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21754:16"/>
And the allowance which we make God in his houſe in our Churches, is that which <hi>Conſtituta diualia permiſerunt Iudaeis,</hi> that which the conſtitutions of the chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours allowed to the Iewes in their ſynagogues: that is, <hi>Tegumen parietibus imponere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caſsiod. lib. <hi>2.</hi> epiſt. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> bare walles, and a couer vpon it to keepe vs from rayne: <hi>Nec aliquid ornatus fas ſit adijcere,</hi> neither is it lawfull to adde any ornament, as was ſaid to the Iewes, except perchance a cuſhion and a waine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcot ſeate, for ones owne eaſe and credite. But where the firſt good chriſtian Emperours ſaid,<note place="margin">Eſay. 9.10.</note> that of Eſay 9. ver. 10. <hi>Lateres ceciderunt, lapide caeſo extruemus,</hi> the oratories which were built in the poorer times of chriſtianitie, are decayed, but we will make them <hi>baſilica,</hi> goodly &amp; ſtately Churches, beiond the pallaces of the greateſt monarches: we that are the children, ſay with <hi>Iudas Iſcarioth,</hi> that the magnificence of churches is but a vaine coſt; we will take the hewen ſtone to build our houſes, a houſe of bricke will ſerue for God; the Cedars are fit for princes pallaces, a roofe of wilde fig trees will ſerue for a church: neither conſidering with the good father <hi>Tertull.</hi> that <hi>pietas eſt pro pietate ſumptus facere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertull. apol. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Godlineſſe to be at coſt with God;</hi> nor with <hi>Theodoricus,</hi> that it ſhould be the purpoſe of a good chriſtian, <hi>Noua conſtruere, ſed amplius vetuſta ſeruare. Caſsiod. lib.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Caſsiod. lib. <hi>3.</hi> epiſt. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>epiſt.</hi> 9. to giue ſomewhat himſelfe, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to maintaine that which is giuen by others.</p>
            <p>Let no man thinke that heares me this day, that this zeale for the houſe of God is any ſpice of ſuperſtition, but a very religious affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, inherent to nature, and true chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, though now for the moſt part blotted out by ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religion and auarice: for you haue heard that God hath had his proper place and proper houſe at all times among his people; you haue heard how his tabernacle was furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by his ſpeciall appointment; how the temple was
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21754:16"/>
adorned by the meanes of <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> his choſen ſeruants, and choſen alſo for that purpoſe; and againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edified and reſtored againe to his former beawtie, &amp; mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence as neere as could be, by <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and others: you haue heard that as ſoone as Emperours and Kings were Chriſtians, they ſpent their time, and their ſubſtance in building &amp; adorning the houſes of God, without feare or regard that their actions might be accompted ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition or Iudaiſme.</p>
            <p>You haue heard that it is not a ceremoniall obſeruation of the old lawe, which were ſaid to be in reſpect of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues <hi>ſine ratione, without reaſon, &amp;</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">In quantum vel aliquid fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurabatur vel excludebatur. Tho. <hi>12.</hi> q. <hi>102.</hi> art. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>habere ratione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine ad aliud, and to depend only vpon ſomewhat elſe;</hi> but as it were a conſtitution in nature, holding one and the ſame reaſon, vnder the Law and vnder the Goſpell. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the moſt learned fathers of thoſe times reaſoned thus, and no doubt ſubſtantially,<note place="margin">De conſecrat. diſt. <hi>1.</hi> Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naculum.</note> 
               <hi>Si Iudaei qui vmbris legis deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiebant, haec faciebant, multò magis nos, quibus veritas pate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facta eſt, &amp; gratia per Ieſum Chriſtum data eſt, templa domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no aedificare, &amp; prout melius poſſumus ornare debemus, &amp;c. If the Iewes vvho liued vnder the ſhadow of the lawe did theſe things; much more vve, to vvhome the truth is diſcouered, and ſaluation imparted by Ieſus Chriſt, muſt build Churches to God, and richly adorne them to our habilitie, &amp;c.</hi> And if this were good arguing, our is yet better, and may deliuer vs from all ſuſpition of poperie: If the Iewes vnder the lawe did theſe things, and the beſt Chriſtians in the primitiue Church did the like alſo, the antiquitie and vniuerſalitie in the Church of God will defend vs, in reſtoring theſe ruines, from ſuſpition of innouation or ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>Moſt true it is, that as the deuotion of the people of God towards the making of the Tabernacle and the furniſhing of it did abound, nay ſo far exceede meaſure, that the wiſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21754:17"/>
men that wrought the worke were forced to cry vnto <hi>Moyſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 36.</note> 
               <hi>Plus offert populus quam neceſſarium eſt: the people bring too much, and more then enough for the vſe of the worke:</hi> whereupon <hi>Moyſes</hi> made this proclamation throughout the hoſt, <hi>Nec vir nec mulier quicquam vltra offerat in opere ſanctuarij:</hi> Let neither man nor woman giue any more to the worke of the Sanctuary. So in the time of Popery, the deuotion of the people and the Princes was ſuch towards the building of Gods houſe, the furniſhing of it, the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of his ſeruants both in goods and in lands, that it did riſe and aſcend <hi>vltra neceſsitatem</hi> (it is <hi>Lyraes</hi> note vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that place) <hi>to more then vvas neceſſarie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lira ſuper <hi>36</hi> Exod.</note> 
               <hi>Imo contra vtilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, nay to more then vvas profitable:</hi> For many abuſed the riches of the Church to worldly pompe and the enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of their friends and kindred, to omit other abuſes which may not be named; ſo that there wanted onely a <hi>Moyſes</hi> to make a proclamation, <hi>Nec vir nec mulier quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam vltra offerat, let neither man nor vvoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offer any more,</hi> and to ſet a ſtint to the peoples deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eſpecially in thoſe places which had enough. But the horſeleach had two daughters in the Clergie, <hi>inordinate deſire of their owne greatnes,</hi> and <hi>inordinate affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their friends and kindred,</hi> which ſtill cryed <hi>Affer, Affer, bring, bring, giue giue:</hi> and if that would not ſerue, would take it by force or elſe by guile, which made <hi>S. Greg.</hi> intend a decree for a meaſure or rate,<note place="margin">Hugo Card. ſuper <hi>36.</hi> Exod. Aug. ſuper <hi>36.</hi> Exod.</note> in thoſe kinde of offerings, as <hi>Hugo Card.</hi> notes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 36. of Exod.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>S. Auſtine</hi> vpon that place of Exod. giues this note, that as thoſe workemen were <hi>wiſe,</hi> that ſaid vnto <hi>Moyſes, Plus offert populus quàm neceſſarium eſt: the people offer more then ynough to the worke:</hi> ſo they were alſo <hi>Sancti moribus, holy and virtuous in their behauiour;</hi> for they might, ſaith he, haue ſuffered the people to giue more then enough,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21754:17"/>
and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues haue ſecretly conuaied it away, <hi>ſed modeſtia prohibuit, vel religio terruit,</hi> but modeſty reſtrained them, or religion terrified them.</p>
            <p>But where is now this modeſtie, this religion: where is this good nature; this religious feare? God required much of vs, the people brought more, <hi>Adeo vt oblata ſufficerent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 36.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ſuperabundarent, ſo that the gifts vvere ſufficient, and too much for the worke,</hi> Exod. 36. the lawes of Mortmaine &amp;c. prouided it ſhould not be lawfull for a man to do what he would with his owne, <hi>&amp; ſic ceſſatum eſt a muneribus offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendis, and ſo the people were ſtayed from offring. Ib.</hi> But had it ſtaid there it had bin well: had the ſuperaboundance bin imployed to good holy vſes, the intent of the <hi>Donors</hi> had not bin made fruſtrate, nor God had bin robbed of that which was his: but the horſeleach had two other daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters among the laietie, <hi>Auaritia, &amp; luxuria, couetouſnes, and riotouſnes,</hi> which haue cryed ſo long <hi>Aufer, Aufer take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, take away,</hi> that they haue not only remoued the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraboundance from the ſtorehouſe or treaſurie of God, <hi>but left neither bread nor meate in his houſe,</hi> Malac. 3.10.<note place="margin">Mala. 3.10.</note> and though our <hi>Moyſes</hi> cry neuer ſo loude by proclamation &amp; ſtatute, <hi>Nec vir nec mulier vltrà auferat; let neither man nor woman purloine any more:</hi> yet <hi>non ceſſatum eſt a muneri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus auferendis: neither man nor vvoman ceaſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſpoile: ſcarſe any abſtaineth from that vvhich is Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is an old complaint, that the houſes of Biſhops and other ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God were giuen <hi>Militibus, Sagittarijs, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listarijs contra ius &amp; fas habitandas, To be inhabited of ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and archers &amp;c. againſt law and right:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 221.</note> it was <hi>S. Bern.</hi> complaint to <hi>Lewis</hi> the King of Fraunce. It is an old com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint that the houſe of God <hi>domus orationis, efficitur ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulum pecoris aut opilionis aut lanificij officina: ſhould be a ſtable, a ſheepecote, or a ſtorehouſe for wooll, &amp;c.</hi> It was the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21754:18"/>
complaint of <hi>Iohan. Sariſ. Policrat. lib.</hi> 7.<note place="margin">Policrat. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ca.</hi> 21. It is an olde complaint that churches ſhould be robbed of their riches and plate; and that they ſhould make to themſelues <hi>Cami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias &amp; faemoralia, ſhirts, breeches, cuſhions, &amp;c.</hi> of the richeſt robes and furniture there.<note place="margin">Vict. Vticen. in hiſt. Vand. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vict. Vticen. in hiſt. Vandalor. li.</hi> 1. It is an old complaint that the children ſhould plow vp their fathers ſepulchers, and there ſow their corne where their fathers were buried;<note place="margin">Suydas.</note> which <hi>Suydas</hi> calleth, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to remoue thoſe things which ſhould not be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: and <hi>Auguſtus</hi> in a meriment ſaid to <hi>Vectius,</hi> that it was <hi>verè patris memorias colere,</hi> ieſting vpon the ambigui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the word <hi>Colere.</hi> It is an old complaint that the Church was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>In direptionem, alijs clàm, alijs palam occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pantibus ea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. to be ſpoiled of euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by might or by ſleight, Policrat. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>ca.</hi> 17.<note place="margin">Policrat. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> It is an old complaint that <hi>munus bene meriti, the reward of good ſeruice to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth,</hi> ſhould be <hi>diſpendium innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis, the Churches dommage, or vtter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caſs. lib. <hi>7.</hi> epiſt. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Caſsi. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 17. It is an old complaint that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces treaſures were rather augmented <hi>Sacerdotum damnis, quàm hoſtiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpolijs: With the harmes of the Prieſts, then with the ſpoile of the enemy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Symm. lib. <hi>10.</hi> epiſt. <hi>54.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Symma. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 54. And it was <hi>Luthers</hi> complaint, that in his time the way to preferment, was to be witty and cunning in finding new ſleights to impoueriſh the Clergie.<note place="margin">Luth. tom. <hi>3.</hi> pag. <hi>133.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Luth tom.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 133. All theſe are old complaints, to complaine of them were now too late. We complaine now, that where in times paſt the goods of the Church were Gods goods, and therefore <hi>res nullius, no man had right or intereſt in them;</hi> now they be <hi>res nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> and therefore <hi>occupantis, his that can catch them:</hi> or elſe we complaine, that whereas heretofore they were Gods goods, and therefore <hi>res nullius,</hi> now they are <hi>res nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae, nothing at all,</hi> as <hi>Rachel</hi> complained of her children, not that they were ſick,<note place="margin">Math. 2.</note> but <hi>that they were not,</hi> and that was a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21754:18"/>
pitiful complaint as the Euangeliſt noteth: And if we may ſay with the ſober maide in <hi>Plautus</hi> to her father,<note place="margin">Plaut. in Perſ.</note> 
               <hi>res noſtrae ſunt pater pauperculae, ſomewhat vve haue, though very little;</hi> yet we complaine of this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Luther</hi> calles it, this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable hunger of that generation that the Wiſe man ſpeakes of Prou. 30.<note place="margin">Prou. 30.</note> that will not be ſatiſfied with the fat of ſo many Monaſteries, Biſhopricks, and impropriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but haue teeth like ſwords, and iawes like kniues, to deuoure that little which is left to God.</p>
            <p>But beloued Chriſtians, take heed of this ſinne and this affection, for it is ſo odious and diſpleaſing to God, that it is an old rule, <hi>voluntas ſola quoad eccleſiam punitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſt. <hi>19.</hi> Anaſtaſius.</note> a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious intent ſhall not eſcape without puniſhment: but for the action what ſtorie ſo auncient, but it yeeldes vs an inſtance? what heathen <hi>in puris naturalibus</hi> but tooke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it?<note place="margin">Carul. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>104.</hi>
               </note> no man of reading and obſeruation but he may ſay with <hi>Carolus Magnus. in Capitul. Carul. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>ca.</hi> 104. <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uimus multa regna &amp; reges eorum propterea cecidiſſe, quia ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſias ſpoliauerunt reſque earum vaſtauerunt, alienarunt, vel deripuerunt, &amp;c.</hi> we haue knowne many Kings and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes vtterly deſtroyed, becauſe they haue ſpoiled and waſted the houſes of God, &amp;c. Shall I tel you that the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then obſerued it? <hi>Virgill</hi> notes that the Graecians offered violence to the Temple of <hi>Pallas;</hi>
               <q>Corripuere ſacram effigiem,<note place="margin">Virg. Aeneid. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> manibuſque cruentis</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Virgineas auſidiuae contingere vittas.</hi> Wherupon he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers this note in particular, which <hi>Carolus</hi> gaue more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally;
<q>Ex illo fluere &amp; retro ſublapſa referri</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spes Danaum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de ciu. Dei lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> More of theſe matters you may find in Saint <hi>Auſtins</hi> booke <hi>de ciu. Dei.</hi> 1. Shall I tell you of the Temple of God built by <hi>Solomon? Ieroboam</hi> and the reſt of the Kings of Iſraell after him, withheld the people from
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21754:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
comming vp to the Temple and offring yeerly vnto God, and thereby withheld a great part of thoſe tithes and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations which were due vnto God. You ſhall finde if you obſerue it, that whereas in the kingdome of <hi>Iudah</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>Dauid</hi> reigned ſucceſſiuely: there were nine chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and nine ſundrie families that reigned in Iſraell: and that the kingdome of Iſraell continued in no one familie, aboue fower generations: which terme ſeemeth to be the time limited by God, for the extirpation of the iſſue of wicked men. <hi>Nabuchodonozor</hi> according to the will of God for the ſinnes of the people, carryed them captiue, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither with them the riches of the Temple and the veſſels thereof; and he eſcaped not puniſhment, as you all know; but he kept them ſo that they might haue beene vſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if occaſion had ſerued. But when <hi>Balthaſar</hi> abuſed them to prophane vſes, then appeared the writing vpon the wall,<note place="margin">Dan. 5.</note> 
               <hi>mene, tekel, Phares,</hi> and the kingdome was cut off from him, and his poſterity for euer. Shall I tell you of the ſecond Temple? <hi>Antiochus</hi> died miſerablie, and at his death confeſſed his ſinne of ſacriledge, that he had taken veſſels of gold and ſiluer from the Church of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.<note place="margin">1. Mac. 6.</note> 1. <hi>Mac.</hi> 6. <hi>Heliodorus</hi> was ſent to rob the Temple of the riches thereof; and there appeared two men from heauen, which whipped him continually, ſo that he lay downe in the Temple deſtitute of all help, til at the requeſt of the ſouldiers the Prieſt prayed for him.<note place="margin">2. Mac. 3.</note> 2. <hi>Mac.</hi> 3. <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey</hi> noted by <hi>Tully</hi> and <hi>Liuy</hi> for one of the moſt fortunate men in the world, after he had abuſed the Temple of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,<note place="margin">Ioſephus.</note> had continually vnhappy ſucceſſe and died miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. The like is obſerued of <hi>Marcus Craſſus</hi> for the ſame reaſon by the ſame author.</p>
            <p>But perchance you imagine that God was the God of the Iewes, and not of the Chriſtians, and was zelous ouer
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21754:19"/>
his houſe and his houſhold vnder the law; but careles of his ſeruice and ſeruants vnder the goſpel. Firſt this is a rule which we learne of him <hi>pro menſura delicti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 25.</note> 
               <hi>erit plaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum modus,</hi> as the treſpaſſe is, ſuch is the puniſhment: and therefore both in the law of God and man, by the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of the puniſhment, we iudge of the qualitie of an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Now what ſinne ſo ſeuerely puniſhed euen in the Apoſtles time as this was. Before any Church was built vnto Chriſt, before any law commaunded to giue to the Church,<note place="margin">Acts. 4.</note> when <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> withheld ſecretly parte of that which voluntarily they had giuen vnto God for the vſe of his ſeruants, they were puniſhed ſeuerely with ſudden death. Acts. 4. Preſently after the Church was endowed and adorned with riches and pretious furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Iulian</hi> was wounded to death with an arrow from heauen when he had robbed the Churches, and ſcoffingly ſaide, <hi>Ecce quam pretioſis vaſis miniſtratur Mariae filio.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theodor. hiſt. eccleſ. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> Are theſe veſſelles fitte for the ſonne of Marie? <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. And when <hi>Thimelicus</hi> a dauncer, had bought by chaunce ſome holy veſtement, and abuſed it publickly in the open theater;<note place="margin">Theodor. hiſt. eccl. lib. <hi>5.</hi> ca. <hi>37.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Theodoret</hi> affirmes him <hi>Subi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tò expiraſſe:</hi> in that very place to haue giuen vp the ghoſt. I paſſe ouer multitudes of exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples in the primitiue church; as alſo <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſecond of latter times, and <hi>Philippe Maria,</hi> and leaue to your wiſe and religious conſideration the ſucceſſe of ſuch men, as haue been vſed as inſtruments to ouerthrow the Church in theſe later times of freſher memory.</p>
            <p>If they which carrie the like affection, and ceaſe not to practiſe the like ill actions to their abilitie,<note place="margin">Iob. 21.</note> 
               <hi>ducunt in bonis dies ſuos,</hi> ſpend their daies in wealth, and their ſeed ſeemeth to be eſtabliſhed in their ſight. <hi>Iob.</hi> 21.<note place="margin">Iob. 12.</note> if as the ſame <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, The tabernacles of robbers do proſper, and they are
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21754:20"/>
in ſafetie that prouoke God? yet we ſay as <hi>Optatus</hi> ſaid to the Donatiſts in the ſame caſe <hi>lib.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Opt. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>An quia ceſſat talis modo vindicta, ideo tibi cum tuis, vindicas innocentiam:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God doth not now puniſh you, becauſe you enioye peaceably thoſe ſpoiles, are you therefore innocent? No, no,<note place="margin">Gloſſ. ord. ſuper <hi>12. Iob.</hi>
               </note> the ordinary gloſſe ſaith excellently, <hi>Aliud miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diter dat Deus, aliud habere ſinit iratus:</hi> it is one thing for God in mercie to bleſſe vs, and another thing to ſuffer vs to be rich in his anger,<note place="margin">Heſiod. lib. <hi>1.</hi> oper.</note> and heauie diſpleaſure: And <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiodus</hi> could make a difference between riches <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: riches which were taken by force and violence, and riches, which were giuen by the bleſſing of God: and
<q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</q>
it is good to be rich by gift, but ill to be rich by rapine: euen an occaſion of death, of ſome ill death; death to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by couetous hourding; and death to the ſonne by rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous ſpending: And as it is a rule in Simonie 500. yeares old <hi>Spiritualium venditores maiori ſemper egeſtate confundi:</hi> that the ſellers of ſpirituall things are pinched at laſt with extreme penurie: ſo it is as olde a rule in ſacriledge, <hi>Quae malignè contraxit pater,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. Ele. ep. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>luxu peiori refundet haeres:</hi> that which the father hath wickedly ſcraped togither, the ſon ſhall more wickedly ſcatter abroad.</p>
            <p>And it is woorth the obſeruing now a daies, that of thoſe goods and landes which are taken from God,
<q>Perpetuus nulli datur vſus, &amp; haeres</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Horat. lib. <hi>2.</hi> ep. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Haeredem alterius, velut vnda ſuperuenit vndam. Horat. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ep.</hi> 2. No man poſſeſſeth them long, but they paſſe from man to man, from heire to heire, from family to fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, like the Arcke of God which could finde no place to reſt in among the Philiſtines, but was remooued from Aſdod,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 5.</note> to Gath, from Gath, to Ekron, and troubled the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21754:20"/>
people whereſoeuer it came, till they returnd it againe to his proper place. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>Wherefore to conclude this point, Honorable, &amp;c. as God in the former times of Chriſtianity, when the church was perſecuted,<note place="margin">Aug. ep. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> would haue that firſt part of the ſecond Pſalme fulfilled <hi>Aſtiterunt reges terrae;</hi> the Kings of the earth ſtood vp, and the Princes tooke counſaile againſt the Lord, and againſt his annointed; and then after would haue that other part perfourmed, <hi>Et nunc reges intelligite;</hi> be wiſe now ye Kings, be learned ye iudges of the earth, &amp;c. in the time of good <hi>Conſtantine:</hi> So alſo ſeeing in theſe latter times the former is againe fulfilled, <hi>Aſtite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt reges terrae;</hi> fulfill alſo this latter part once againe, <hi>Et nunc reges intelligite,</hi> and once againe vnderſtand and know you that be magiſtrates and gouernours and gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp;c. that God as the very law of nature teacheth, and all ſtates and ages of the Church haue practiſed, challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth an intereſt in all our goods, our lands and poſſeſſions; that this is paide as a kinde of tribute, and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his ſoueraigne dominion ouer vs: That he accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them not becauſe he hath neede of them, but for an endleſſe continuance of religion amongſt vs; which by experience we finde to decay with them: That he hath diſpoſed them partly for an ornament to his houſe, partly for the neceſſarie vſe of his ſeruice, &amp; partly for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of his ſeruants and miniſters: That we receiue the poſſeſſion of them immediately from you, and but me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from him; but receiue the right of them, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from him, and but mediately from you: who gaue them to God, and he vnto vs, Num. 18.<note place="margin">Num. 18.</note> That he hath bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thoſe Princes and their poſterities, which haue thus honored him with part of their goods: and promiſed to open the windowes of heauen and powre downe immea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21754:21"/>
bleſſings, vpon the people that in this reſpect delt truely with him,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. that he hath reuenged himſelfe on them that robbed him in themſelues and their poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: &amp; curſed with a curſe whole nations that ſpoiled him, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Mal. 3.</note> That the time hath been when there was ſcarcely one Chriſtian to be found ſo wicked, that durſt offer vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to the houſe of God, or the furniture of it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Iewes were hired to ſpoile it,<note place="margin">In vita Bern. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in vita Bernard.</hi> That in theſe latter times it was not ſpoiled by Wolues &amp; Lions ſuch as proudly bid battel to God: but by Foxes, who by ſleight, and by holy pretences, and by colour of friendſhip would ſtrip him of all:<note place="margin">Bern. Sen. <hi>65.</hi> ſuper Cant. <hi>Pſal. 77.</hi>
               </note> but as Saint <hi>Bern.</hi> ſaieth of ſuch Foxes, <hi>poſteriora eorum foetent. Ser.</hi> 65. conſider their owne end or their poſteritie, and you wil ſay with the Pſal. 77. that our God <hi>percuſsit inimicos in poſteriora:</hi> hath woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his enimies on the hinder parts.</p>
            <p>Wherefore <hi>nunc reges intelligite,</hi> you that be magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, gouernors, &amp;c. at length vnderſtand and be wiſe, and learne to diſcerne betweene ſpirituall things and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things, <hi>inter <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, betweene that you take by force, and that which God giueth in mercie; <hi>inter <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pindarus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pind.</note> betweene purchaſe and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie: betweene holy things and prophane things: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the goods of God which are perpetuall, and the ſubſtance of men, which are truely called mooueables, and ſubiect to ſale and alienation: And when you craue, begge not that which is Gods; and when you giue, giue not that which is Gods; and when you buie, buie not that which is Gods; and when you ſell, ſell not that which is Gods: Let other mens harmes be inſtructions for you, and other mens puniſhments be cautious for you: let other mens vertues be your examples; and religious Princes your pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns and precedents. Holy <hi>Dauid,</hi> wiſe <hi>Solomon,</hi> religious
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21754:21"/>
               <hi>Constantine,</hi> and our holy, wiſe and religious Princeſſe, of whom we may giue this teſtimonie to all ſucceeding ages, that <hi>Petrus Bleſenſ.</hi> left to her moſt noble progenitor <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. <hi>Benedictus dominus qui regem Henricum a talibus hacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus conſeruauit innoxium:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. Bleſ. ep. <hi>10</hi>
               </note> Bleſſed be that God which hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hath defended her Maieſtie from all kinde of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that hath not furniſhed her houſe with the ſpoile of the Church, nor increaſed her reuenew by the loſſe of Gods houſe; that hath not defiled her hands with <hi>Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> nor beſtowed her preferments for perſonall fauour, or reſpect of reward: wherefore <hi>Magnificauit eam Dominus in conſpectu regum;</hi> God hath magnified her in the ſight of the Princes of the earth, and hath giuen her a treaſure which will neuer be ſpent; euen an honorable name, and bleſſed memorie to all poſteritie.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing I obſerued, was the end and vſe of this houſe, and that was to pray in: <hi>My houſe ſhall be called the houſe of prayer.</hi> Churches as euery thing elſe receiue their chiefe perfection from the ende whereunto they ſerue. Now the end and vſe of Churches is, the publike ſeruice and worſhip of God: which publike ſeruice in this place is comprehended vnder the name of prayer: becauſe of all religious actions, prayer is reckoned the firſt and the chiefe:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thom.</hi> 22. <hi>q.</hi> 83. <hi>art.</hi> 3.</note> for <hi>ſicut mens humana praeeminet exterio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus &amp; corporalibus membris, vel exterioribus rebus, quae ad Dei ſeruitium applicantur: ita etiam oratio praeeminet alijs actibus religionis:</hi> as the ſoule of a man excels his body, and all the parts thereof, and all other externall things, which are vſed to the ſeruice of God; ſo prayer excels all other religious actions. And that this was the chiefe end of Churches, of thoſe houſes which were built to God; both the name argues which God impoſed, and as we ſay chriſtened it with, <hi>domus mea domus orationis vocabitur;</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:21754:22"/>
and the very words which <hi>Salomon</hi> vſed in the dedication of it 3. Reg. 8.29. and the practiſe which <hi>Ioel</hi> notes,<note place="margin">3. Reg. 8.29. Ioel. 2.17.</note> 2.17. that the Prieſts ſhould weepe betweene the porch and the altar, and ſay, Spare thy people, O Lord, &amp;c. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though other things were there practiſed, as offering of ſacrifices, and oblations, burning of incenſe, &amp;c. yet thoſe alſo are comprehended vnder <hi>S. Paules</hi> diſtinction, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> ſupplications, interceſſions, or thanks-geuings, 1. Tim. 2. for all the ſacrifices and offerings were <hi>gratiarum actio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> thanks-geuings vnto God.</p>
            <p>And that our Churches now in Chriſtianitie are both <hi>domus dei,</hi> and <hi>domus orationis,</hi> houſes for God, and hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for prayer, the names import which in the pureſt times were giuen to theſe places: for they were called in the primitiue Church <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>dominica,</hi> Gods houſes; and <hi>oratoria,</hi> places eſpecially deuoted to prayer: Though in later times <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are become <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in ſome places, not for their ſtatelines, as in the time of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> but for the proprietie &amp; poſſeſſion of them; and <hi>oratoria</hi> are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into <hi>auditoria;</hi> oratories into auditories: and where the Apoſtles, who had in their commiſſion <hi>Ite praedicate,</hi> goe, preach, put prayer in the firſt place before preaching Act. 6. <hi>Nos orationi &amp; miniſterio verbi inſtantes erimus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 6.</note> We will be inſtant in prayer &amp; preaching the word: now we ſay,<note place="margin">Confeſs. Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetica.</note> 
               <hi>Cedant potiores partes in coetibus ſacris doctrinae e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelicae, caueatur<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ne nimis prolixis precibus fatigetur in coetu populus:</hi> let the firſt and the chiefe place be giuen to preaching; and a prouiſo is made, that the people be not ouerwearyed with too much praying. And though the Church of England hath no ſuch conſtitution, yet the people entertaine the practiſe of it, many of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning common prayer, but a greater part neglecting them, and holding it the only exerciſe of the ſeruice of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21754:22"/>
God to heare a Sermon.</p>
            <p>But beloued for your inſtruction, you ſhall vnderſtand that this is an old error, not now firſt ſprung vp, or proper and peculiar to this age only:<note place="margin">Chry. Hom. <hi>3.</hi> de incompre. dei naturae.</note> for <hi>S. Chryſoſt.</hi> complaines that the multitude of people that came to his ſermons, and heard him with great attention, was <hi>ingens &amp; penè inaudita,</hi> great and almoſt incredible; that they were ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to approch neere to heare him, that patiently they would expect the end of his ſermon: but at the time of prayer and of miniſtration of the ſacraments and chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian myſteries, then <hi>vacua deſerta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eccleſia reddebatur,</hi> the church was emptie and forſaken of all. And that you may heare me with the better patience, you ſhall vnderſtand that it is no new reproofe: <hi>S. Chryſoſt.</hi> cryed out, <hi>proh fidem hominum chriſtianorum, quo pacto iſtaec veniam conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur?</hi> he calleth the very faith and profeſſion of chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to witneſſe againſt it, and reckoned it a fault that would hardly be pardoned.</p>
            <p>Was this a fault then? and is it a vertue now; was it then reproueable, and now commendable? if it be, ſhew me ſome practiſe in the people of God. Vnder the law of nature men were moued to the worſhip of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thom.</hi> 3. <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>art.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>nulla lege exterius data, ſed ſolo interiori inſtinctu,</hi> not by any exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lawe or externall inſtruction, but only by a naturall and inward motion: wherefore then the houſe of God could not be the houſe of hearing, but of praying, ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and deuine worſhip.<note place="margin">Gen. 22.5.</note> In the time of <hi>Abraham</hi> the whole ſeruice of God was comprehended vnder the name of inuocation, or adoration: When by the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſion of man the law of nature was ſo obſcured, that it was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary an externall lawe ſhould be giuen, yet becauſe it was more corrupted <hi>quoad appetitum boni, quàm quoad cognitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem veri,</hi> the place appointed for the ſeruice and worſhip
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21754:23"/>
of God, whether it were Tabernacle or Temple, was <hi>domus orationis,</hi> the houſe of prayer: hearing the law expounded, was but the way to knowledge, and knowledge the way to the worſhip of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tho.</hi> 1. <hi>q.</hi> 117. <hi>art.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>via ad cultum:</hi> for <hi>ſcientia non eſt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litas actiua, ſed principium quo aliquis dirigitur in operando,</hi> Knowledge is no actiue quality, but a meanes to direct vs to, and in the ſeruice of God. In the times of Chriſtianitie the houſes of God were <hi>oratoria,</hi> not <hi>auditoria:</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were built the Apoſtles in their times vſed this temple as the houſe of prayer:<note place="margin">Act. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> went vp to the temple to pray, Act. 2. and <hi>S. Paule</hi> preſently after his conuerſion went vp for to pray: And our Sauiour told the people parables to this end, that they ought alwayes to pray,<note place="margin">Luc. 18.1. 1. Theſ. 5.17.</note> Luc. 18.1. and <hi>S. Paule</hi> in plaine termes without parable expreſſeth it, <hi>Indeſinenter orate,</hi> pray continually. No ſuch teſtimony giuen to hearing, which is not perfect in it ſelfe, but ordained to a farther end and purpoſe: and therefore when the parents were commaunded to teach their children the lawe, that was not the end of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, but they muſt teach the lawe that they may learne how to feare the Lord,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.</note> or ſerue the Lord: And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Prieſts were commaunded to teach the people, the commaundement reſted not there, but they muſt teach the lawes that the people might learne them, and take heede to obſerue them: And therefore the proteſtation of the people vnto the Prieſt was this,<note place="margin">Deut. 5.</note> Declare thou to vs that which God ſaith, and we will heare it and do it. And therefore the bleſſing is not promiſed to hearing, but to doing,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> 
               <hi>non auditores verbi ſed factores &amp;c.</hi> God reckoneth not ſo much of auditors as factors, of thoſe that heare his word,<note place="margin">Luc. 11.</note> as of thoſe that keepe his word: And bleſſed is he that heares the word of God, but with this condition, ſo that he keepe it. Otherwiſe the hearing of the lawe or the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21754:23"/>
Goſpell to know onely, or to know more then another, <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſaith is the mother of pride, <hi>ſcientia inflat:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.</note> The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſay it is <hi>Diabolica tentatio,</hi> the temptation wherewith the Deuill aſſaulted our firſt parents in Paradice: The Schoolemen ſay it is ſuperfluitie at leaſt, if not ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for this is a rule in diuinitie, that euery religious action which conſiſteth only in <hi>exterioribus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thom.</hi> 22. <hi>q.</hi> 93. <hi>art.</hi> 2.</note> and is not referred <hi>ad interiorem dei cultum,</hi> to the inward ſeruice of God, is either ſuperfluous, or ſuperſtitious.</p>
            <p>I hope no man that heares me this day will be ſo iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to me, or preiudiciall to his owne knowledge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, as to conceiue that I ſpeake againſt hearing or frequenting of Sermons: for I know, and would haue you all learne it, that <hi>principium rectè viuendi eſt rectè au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire; the ordinarie meanes to liue well, is to heare well;</hi> and <hi>ſcire eſt via, cauſa &amp; medium ad amare: to know God is the way, the cauſe and the meanes to loue God:</hi> and that <hi>bonum intellectum</hi> goodnes and vertue well vnderſtoode, is the obiect of our will, which will is the ſubiect of charitie; and therefore the better you know God, the apter you are to loue him actually: And if I ſhould denye it, yet nature would tell you <hi>quibus ſuffragijs exoptata pietas audiatur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Symm. lib. <hi>1.</hi> epiſt. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> with what applauſe an holy and deuoute ſermon is enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. But I complaine that you, who are admitted now long ago to the fellowſhip of chriſtianitie, and bound and ſworne to obſerue the lawes and cuſtomes thereof, and are now no longer probationers <hi>catechumeni,</hi> hearers chate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſts, ſhould now prefer hearing before praying; knowing before doing, wherein conſiſts the ſeruice and worſhip of God; ſeeing the actuall ſeruice and worſhip of God is the end, and hearing but the meanes to that end: and the rule is <hi>Semper finis excellit id quod eſt ad finem.</hi> I complaine not that our Churches are auditories, but that they are not
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21754:24"/>
oratories: not that you come to Sermons, but that you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe or neglect common prayer; not that you reſort <hi>ad porticum Solomonis,</hi> to Paules croſſe, but that your pariſh churches are naked and emptie. I complaine not that you haue ready and attentiue eares, but that you haue not pure hands, humble lookes, ſingle eyes, cleane harts, ſoules and bodies vndefiled. I complaine that your hearing is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly a cloake to couer and conceale your want of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a nurſe to your ſlothfulnes, which cannot endure the true labour of praying. I complaine that you heare much and profit little, which the learned hold for a ſigne of reprobation,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.</note> and <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſaith little leſſe, Heb. 6. <hi>The earth which hath drunke in the raine which comes oft vpon it, and yet brings forth thornes and bryers, is reproued, and nigh vnto curſing.</hi> I complaine that the end of your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring is to cenſure the preacher, not <hi>gaudere ſuper cohorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 15.31.</note> Act. 15.31. to reioyſe or make benefit of that which is heard. In a word, I complaine, and I complaine not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, that all the ſeruice of God is reduced only to hearing of Sermons; and our hearing applied to knowledge only.</p>
            <p>But beloued Chriſtians, the ſeruice of God was not wont to be referred to hearing; but hearing referred to the ſeruice of God: nor the ſcope of Chriſtianitie was not to know; but the ſcope of knowledge was to be good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: Chriſtian religion was not onely to know without error; but alſo to liue without ſpot: and therefore though <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſaith <hi>Christus factus eſt nobis ſapientia:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30.</note> Chriſt is made wiſedome vnto vs, yet he ſtaieth not there as though Chriſtianitie conſiſted in knowledge only; but he addeth alſo <hi>factus eſt iuſtitia, &amp; ſanctificatio, &amp; redemptio:</hi> he is made our righteouſnes, ſanctification, and redemption. 1. Cor. 1.30. <hi>Sapientia in intellectu, iustitia in voluntate, ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificatio in opere, redemptio in ſtatu:</hi> wiſedome in our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21754:24"/>
righteouſnes in our will; ſanctification in our workes; and redemption to the whole man, <hi>Caiet.</hi> And therefore in the perfecteſt time of Chriſtianitie, hearing was not inough to make one reputed a good Chriſtian, no nor Baptiſme added to it; for hearing was before Baptiſme; nor beleefe ioyned to them both: what not hearing of ſermons, not baptiſme, not beleefe a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent argument of true Chriſtianitie? why then what ſhall be thought of vs? no, that was not then inough. It is ſaid in the 8. of the Acts. that <hi>Simon Magus</hi> beleeued,<note place="margin">Act 8.</note> and was baptiſed, and did cleaue faſt to <hi>Philip,</hi> followed <hi>Philip</hi> and was a diligent auditor of his; and yet <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was neuer good Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>The iſſue of al that I intende to ſpeake if the time ſerued is this. The houſe of God is called the houſe of prayer, either becauſe all diuine ſeruice is comprehended vnder the name of prayer, or ſome <hi>Species</hi> of prayer; or els be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of all diuine duties prayer is the chiefe; or elſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in all actions of Chriſtianitie and religion which are perfourmed in the houſe of God, prayer is euer one and an eſpeciall part: As in baptiſme, in the ſacrament of the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, in matrimonie, in churching of women, in burying the dead, in preaching the word; beſides the ordinary action of common prayer it ſelfe which is as <hi>iuge ſacrificium,</hi> the ſacrifice which God requireth euerie day, not only priuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our chamber, but eſpecially togither in the Church of God. Preaching alſo is a part <hi>diuini cultus</hi> of the ſeruice of God, and therefore hath a reward: but hearing onely; or hearing to know, without an intent to practiſe; is but the way to knowledge, and knowledge it ſelfe but <hi>via ad cultum,</hi> the way and the meanes to the ſeruice of God: and therfore if it ſtay there it hath no reward: for not the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers onely, but the dooers are bleſſed of God. And
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21754:25"/>
therefore in the primitiue Church ſome were admitted to heare, which were not admitted to the publicke ſeruice of God, and were called <hi>Catechumeni</hi> hearers or catechiſts, a name of imperfection.</p>
            <p>Thankes be to God for it, you are not as heathen to be taught of vs, <hi>Quid oporteat credere:</hi> what you muſt beleeue to be ſaued: nor as Catechiſts lately conuerted: <hi>Quid opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teat facere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 9.</note> what you muſt doe: as S. <hi>Paule</hi> cryed to God, Acts 9. you know what to beleeue, you know what to do: the ende of our preaching ſhould be eſpecially <hi>mouere,</hi> to mooue and exhort you to practiſe that which you know muſt be done: not becauſe you haue <hi>plenitudinem cognitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> fulnes of knowlegde (ah laſſe we haue it not our ſelues) but becauſe you haue a ſufficiencie of knowledge. And if <hi>Marcus Agrippa</hi> who was no foole but <hi>vir ingentis ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Senec. ep. <hi>94.</hi>
               </note> a man both of courage and wit, was woont to ſay that he owed much to <hi>Saluſt</hi> for this one ſentence, <hi>Concordia paruaeres creſcunt, diſcordia maximae dilabuntur,</hi> by peace &amp; concord ſmall things growe great; by diſſention and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord great things decay; becauſe by that ſentence onely he was made <hi>optimus frater, &amp; optimus amicus,</hi> a very good brother, and a very good friend: I doubt not but the moſt ignorant among you is indebted already to vs for ſo many ſentences, as being well digeſted and practiſed would make you good parents, good children, good friendes, good brethren, good neighbours, good ſubiects, in a word, good Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the abuſe of the Temple, is borrowed of the prophet <hi>Ierem. cap.</hi> 7. where the ſame aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion is vſed, but by way of interrogation: <hi>Is this houſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a den of theeues, whereupon my name is called before your eies? Behold, euen I ſee it, ſaith the Lord.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay; yea certainely it is become a den of theeues. The ſinnes
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21754:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
which the prophet there reproues are, <hi>theft, murther, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery; falſe ſwearing, Idolatrie:</hi> which being vſuall among the people, they would neuertheleſſe <hi>come and ſtand before him in this houſe of his.</hi> And for theeues and murtherers and adulterers and falſe ſwearers and Idolaters, to come into the houſe of God, either to pray or to offer ſacrifice, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a conſtant intent to amende their ill waies, is to make the houſe of God or the houſe of prayer, <hi>a den of theeues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may ſeeme to ſome men, that this Scripture is not well alleaged by our Sauiour Chriſt: who applieth that to buyers and ſellers, that the prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſpeaketh of theeues, murtherers, adulterers, falſe ſweares, &amp; Idolaters. May it pleaſe you therefore to vnderſtand, that in the new Teſtament, the texts &amp; propheſies of the old Teſtament, are alleaged ſomtimes properly &amp; according to the litteral <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſenſe, as in the 1. of <hi>Math.</hi> that propheſie of the 7. of <hi>Eſay: Behold a virgin ſhall conceiue and beare a ſon.</hi> Sometime not properly &amp; litterally, but to expreſſe ſome truth which was <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> ſignified or ſhadowed by them: as in the 1. to the Heb. that of the 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. <hi>I wil be his father &amp; he ſhal be my Son;</hi> which being properly ſpoken of <hi>Salomon,</hi> is applied by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to our Sauiour Chriſt, whoſe life &amp; figure <hi>Salomon</hi> was: as alſo in the 19. of S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpell that of the 12. of Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, <hi>Os non co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minuetis ex eo,</hi> Not a bone of him ſhal be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: which being ſpoken litterally of the lambe, the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt applies to our Sauiour, who was figured by the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> lambe. Sometime neither litterally, neither yet to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe any thing ſignified by it, but rather to note ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what like vnto it, and of ſuch nature, that the Scripture may ſeeme as trulie to be verified of the one as the other: as that which the prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaide of the Iewes in his time, <hi>populus hic labijs me honorat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 29.</note> &amp;c. this people honour me with their lips, Chriſt applieth as if it had been ſpoken
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21754:26"/>
in the ſame caſe of the Iewes in his time, Hypocrites, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> propheſied well of you, ſaying, &amp;c. <hi>Math.</hi> 15. the like example you haue <hi>Math.</hi> 13.14. and Acts. 28.26.</p>
            <p>According to this laſt rule that which the prophet <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> vſeth againſt theeues, murtherers, falſe ſwearers, &amp;c. our Sauiour very well applieth againſt buyers and ſellers, and money changers, and merchandizers; as though theft and forſwearing and merchandizing were all one; which he ſeemeth to implie, ſeeing in this place caſting out the buyers &amp; ſellers, &amp;c. he tels them that they made <hi>the houſe of God a den of theeues:</hi> but in the ſecond of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> performing the like action vpon the ſame kinde of men, he telleth them, that they had made <hi>the houſe of God, a houſe of merchandice:</hi> ſo that with our Sauiour a denne of theeues, and an houſe of merchandice, ſeemeth to admit very ſmall difference.</p>
            <p>And peraduenture the applying of thoſe two phraſes, <hi>a den of theeues,</hi> and <hi>an houſe of merchandice,</hi> to one and the ſelfe ſame fault; moued <hi>S. Chryſoſt.</hi> or the <hi>author operis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfecti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom.</hi> 38. <hi>ſuper</hi> Mattd.</note> the rather to vſe this aſſertion: <hi>Nullus Chriſtianus debet eſſe mercator: aut ſi voluerit, proijciatur de eccleſia.</hi> No Chriſtian man ſhould be a merchandizer; but if he will needes be, let him be caſt out of the Church: which rule though he reſtraine to thoſe that buye their wares and ſell them againe, <hi>integra &amp; immutata,</hi> in the ſame kinde and nature wherein they bought them; excluding them that change the nature of their wares, and ſo ſel againe <hi>non rem ipſam, ſed artificium ſuum;</hi> not the ſelfe ſame, but their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and skill &amp; myſterie:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>annot.</hi> 187.</note> and <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> reſtraines it to Ingroſſers and Monopolies, calling this only merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing &amp; negotiation, according to <hi>Caſsiodore ſuper Pſal.</hi> 70. <hi>quae vilius poſsint comparari, carius velle diſtrahere;</hi> by arte &amp; cunning to raiſe the price of thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, which by
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21754:26"/>
courſe would be much cheaper. And ſome ſchoolemen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine it to thoſe merchants that intend gaine and lucre,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tho.</hi> 22. <hi>q.</hi> 77.</note> as the onely and laſt end of all their labours; and not the maintaynig of their familie, the reliefe of the poore, or the publicke vtilitie of the common wealth: yet ſeeing in theſe latter auaritious daies, for the moſt part, lucre onely, <hi>quod terminum neſcit, ſed in infinitum tendit,</hi> is the common and ordinarie end of merchandizing, of buying and ſelling; and he that is <hi>negotiator auidus,</hi> a couetous merchant, as <hi>S. Auſt.</hi> notes, <hi>pro damno blaſphemat, pro pretijs rerum menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; peierat:</hi> In his loſſes will blaſpheme, and lye, ſweare, and forſweare in the prices of wares: there is now alſo for the moſt part, no great difference betweene a denne of theeues and an houſe of Merchandice.</p>
            <p>Now as our Sauiour applied that which <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſpake of theeues and forſwearers, &amp;c. to buyers and ſellers and merchandizers; becauſe there vſeth to be ſome likeneſſe and affinitie betweene them; ſo the ancient fathers to this imitation, haue applyed this ſaying of our Sauiour Chriſt, to many other ſorts of men: which buie and ſell, rob and ſteale, in the houſe of God; or buie and ſell, rob, and ſteale from the houſe of God. Saint <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> ſaieth that they make the houſe of God a den of theeues which talke and diſcourſe in the Church,<note place="margin">Hom. <hi>36.</hi> in <hi>1.</hi> ad Cor.</note> and driue their bargaines at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſeruice: and concludeth that the Church is not <hi>ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrina, forum, caupona,</hi> a barbars ſhop, an exchang, or a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, but <hi>locus angelorum, locus archangelorum, regia Dei, coelum ipſum:</hi> the place of angels, yea of archangels, the very pallace of God, and heauen itſelfe.</p>
            <p>The whole courſe of fathers and ſchoolemen applie it to buiers and ſellers of eccleſiaſticall orders; to buiers and ſellers of the cures of ſoules, which is a ſpeciall gift and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the holy Ghoſt: of which I haue ſpoken ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21754:27"/>
largely before.<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potian.</note> Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> applies it, <hi>negotiatori clerico,</hi> to a cleargie man that vſeth buying and ſelling and merchandizing, and ſaith that he is <hi>tanquam peſtis fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endus,</hi> to be ſhunned as one infected with the plague, or a leproſie, as a theefe or a robber, lurking and ſhrowding himſelfe in the houſe of God. The ordinarie gloſſe applies it to murther and bloodſhed committed in the Church, which was grieuouſlie puniſhed in the Canon lawe, 24. 1. <hi>qui contra:</hi> and doth portend ſome great ill to the Church or common wealth;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. hiſt. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> as is noted by <hi>Socrates,</hi> and I haue touched it before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioannes Sarisbur,</hi> applies it to them, which alienate Churches, and Eccleſiaſticall houſes with the appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances to lay men: The houſe of prayer, ſayth he, is made an houſe of merchandize,<note place="margin">De nugis curial. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Domino prohibente,</hi> which is forbidden by God himſelfe, and the temple which hath the foundation <hi>in lapide adiutorij,</hi> 1. Sam. 4.1. <hi>on the ſtone of help,</hi> is turned into a denne of theeues: and his reaſon is this, <hi>Siquidem eccleſia data eſt in direptionem, &amp;c.</hi> for the houſe of God, and the appurtenances are layd waſt, and made the poſſeſſions of mightie or ſubtile men.</p>
            <p>But this laſt ſorte of men in my opinion, may be ſaid to make the houſe of God worſe then a denne of theeues, (if worſe may be) becauſe whereas the other ſorts rob, and ſpoyle in the houſes of God; theſe rob and ſpoyle the houſes of God, and alienate and alter the proprietie of them; and of the poſſeſſions and inheritance of God, make them the poſſeſſions and inheritance of theeues: For whereas all good Chriſtians ſay with the Prophet <hi>Dauid, Vnam petij a domino,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. One thing I haue deſired of the Lord, and that I vvill require, euen that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord all the dayes of my life:</hi> to what end? <hi>to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the beawtie of the Lord, and to viſite his temple;</hi> that is
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21754:27"/>
ſaith <hi>Lyra, ad adorandum ibidem frequenter, &amp; offerendum, that he might dayly vvorſhip him there, and offer ſacrifices to him:</hi> theſe men ſay <hi>Vnum petij a domino (de praeterito) I haue made one ſuite now a great vvhile, to my Lord or mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, &amp;c. Et hanc requiram (de futuro) I vvill vrge this ſuite till I haue obteined it: vt inhabitem in domo domini, &amp;c. that I may dwell in ſome of Gods houſes all the dayes of my life, and my children after me:</hi> to what ende? <hi>vt haereditate poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deam ſanctuarium domini,</hi> as the wicked men ſayd Pſal. 83. that ſome of Gods lands or ſome of Gods houſes may be my inheritance for euer and euer. So that where they that abuſe the houſe of God with ſundry prophanations, and rob and ſteale and merchandiſe in it, make it <hi>ſpeluncam la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronum,</hi> a denne for a time to lurke in, and not be ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of ſuch behauiour: they that rob and ſpoyle God of his houſes, and alienate them to their prophane vſes, do make of them <hi>tabernacula praedonum,</hi> Iob. 12. not only the dennes, but the very habitation and dwellings of theeues and robbers.</p>
            <p>Now to conclude; I ſaye with <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> vpon theſe words, <hi>But you haue made it a denne of theeues: Vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam de praeterito populo eſſet tantùm dictum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom.</hi> 13. <hi>ſuper</hi> Marc.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I would to God it could haue beene ſayd only of the Iewes, and not of the Chriſtians; I would to God it could haue bene applyed to Chriſtians heretofore, and not vnto vs; <hi>Plora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remus quidem illos, ſed de nobis gauderemus, vve vvould la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ouer them, but reioyſe for our ſelues:</hi> but now in many places, and in many reſpects, nay in all theſe reſpects, the houſe of God is made a houſe of merchandize, the houſe of prayer is made a denne of theeues. Theſe things are ſo manifeſt, that they require neither expoſition, nor application; I would to God they were more obſcure, and hidden from vs, and that we did not maintaine theſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21754:28"/>
prophanations, by pretences, and long cuſtomes, as theſe Ievves did. Wherefore if we lament ouer them, we haue cauſe to weepe and howle for our ſelues, who haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as great increaſe and ſtrength to theſe ſinnes, as time hath added yeares and increaſe to the world: ſo that theſe iniquities being now at the full ripeneſſe and perfect growth (which argue little true faith, and leſſe true chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, if leſſe may be, vpon the face of the earth) we are to expect a perfect and finall reformation from Chriſt Ieſus of theſe abuſes; not by peſtilence, famine, warres, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or fires from heauen, &amp;c. his ordinarie inſtruments, which do moue vs but little: but from his owne hands, not armed with a whip, or other temporall puniſhment, as at his firſt comming,<note place="margin">Math. 3.</note> but with his fanne, wherewith he will make cleane the floore of his Church, and gather the wheate into his garner, and burne vp the chaffe of all theſe inquities, with vnquenchable fire. To this Ieſus, the moſt iealous patron of the houſe of his Father, and the moſt iuſt iudge of the quick &amp; the dead, together with the Father, &amp; the holy Ghoſt, three perſons, and one almighty and euer-liuing God, be aſcribed all honor, glorie, praiſe, and dominion, for euer and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21754:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
